<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Valentin Manès</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Valentin Manès</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/profile_valentin.png</url>
      <title>Valentin Manès</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>AskPoker.ai Dev Log #2: Building a Content Engine and Finding My Market</title>
      <link>/devlog/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/devlog/2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Week 2 of building 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://askpoker.ai&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AskPoker.ai&lt;/a&gt; in public. This week: technical progress, content creation infrastructure, and a strategic market pivot.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;technical-progress-building-the-data-pipeline&#34;&gt;Technical Progress: Building the Data Pipeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week&amp;rsquo;s experiments made it clear I needed better data from my solver to create meaningful content. So I built a comprehensive evaluation function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;type EvalReport struct {
    ActionEVs []float32  // Expected value for each possible action
    Equity    float32    // Current hand equity
    EQRs      []float32  // Equity realization by action
    AvgPolicy []float64  // Solver&#39;s recommended action frequencies
    AvgEquity float32    // Average equity across opponent range
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gives me everything needed to explain &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; a play is optimal, not just &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; to do. I wrote a script that runs this for every decision point in a hand, creating a complete strategic narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-bottleneck&#34;&gt;The Bottleneck&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s where past shortcuts caught up with me. Generating game states by sampling from subgames is painfully slow. Why? A month ago, I took a shortcut in how I handle range distributions. Instead of maintaining explicit range objects with hand probabilities, I used a simpler approach that now makes sampling computationally expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fix is straightforward – properly maintain range objects throughout the calculation. But it means rewriting a chunk of the solver infrastructure. For now, turn and river analysis is essentially broken, limiting me to flop-only content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to defer this fix. Why spend days on technical debt when I still need to validate whether anyone wants this product?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;content-creation-engine-from-data-to-articles&#34;&gt;Content Creation Engine: From Data to Articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of perfecting the solver, I built a content generation pipeline:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Generation&lt;/strong&gt;: Run EvalHand for each decision point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;: Feed each situation to an LLM for strategic interpretation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outline Creation&lt;/strong&gt;: Combine solver data + manual context → LLM creates article outline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Human Review&lt;/strong&gt;: I review and adjust the outline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Draft Generation&lt;/strong&gt;: LLM writes the first draft&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final Edit&lt;/strong&gt;: Human polish and fact-checking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process works. I published two deep-dive analyses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.askpoker.ai/blog/montenegro-444k-pot&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Montenegro&amp;rsquo;s $444k pot breakdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.askpoker.ai/blog/100k-pocket-tens-that-refused-to-die&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;$100k pocket tens analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Images are still manual (screenshots, generated images), and there&amp;rsquo;s an annoying OpenGraph bug to fix, but the core pipeline produces solid content. Each piece takes about 2-3 hours from data to published article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;Screenshot of AskPoker.ai blog showing two poker hand analysis articles: &#39;The $100,000 Pocket Tens That Refused to Die&#39; featuring pocket tens cards and poker chips, and &#39;The $444,000 Flush Draw That Changed Everything&#39; showing a live poker table at Triton Montenegro with players in action&#34;
    src=&#34;/img/blogs.jpg&#34; width=&#34;600px&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;strategic-market-pivot-narrowing-focus&#34;&gt;Strategic Market Pivot: Narrowing Focus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week forced a reality check on my market ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original vision&lt;/strong&gt;: Target US/global cash games – the biggest poker market. These games typically run 7-9 players with varying stack sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The problems&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My solver only handles 5-max games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t actually play these formats (French platforms are segregated)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical complexity scales exponentially with more players&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m building for a market I don&amp;rsquo;t understand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New direction&lt;/strong&gt;: French 3-player Spin &amp;amp; Go tournaments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s a smaller market. But consider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 players instead of 9 (dramatically simpler to solve)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Short stacks (less strategic complexity)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most popular format in France&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I actually play this format daily&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This feels like a retreat, but it&amp;rsquo;s strategic. Better to build something that works for a market I understand than to fail chasing a larger opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-well-expand-later-trap&#34;&gt;The &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;ll Expand Later&amp;rdquo; Trap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m aware of the risk. Countless startups say &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rsquo;ll expand later&amp;rdquo; and become trapped in their initial niche. Their product-market fit becomes so specific that expansion requires starting over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But poker might be different. The core challenge isn&amp;rsquo;t teaching French players different rules – it&amp;rsquo;s getting anyone to trust AI coaching. If I can prove French players will take strategic advice from an AI, that psychological validation should transfer across markets. The technical details (game formats, stack sizes) are engineering problems. Trust is the real barrier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;next-focus-tiktok-experimentation&#34;&gt;Next Focus: TikTok Experimentation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blog posts are live but not promoted – they&amp;rsquo;re raw material for the next experiment. This week I&amp;rsquo;m pivoting to TikTok content creation. Poker strategy performs well in short-form video, and it&amp;rsquo;s where my target audience actually spends time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan: Transform blog analyses into bite-sized video content. Test what resonates. Learn what hooks work. Then scale what succeeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;looking-ahead&#34;&gt;Looking Ahead&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 2 taught me to embrace constraints. My solver can&amp;rsquo;t handle everything, so I&amp;rsquo;ll focus on what it can. The global market is too broad, so I&amp;rsquo;ll start with France. Perfect technical solutions can wait until after market validation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next week: Results from TikTok experiments and the eternal question – when do I fix that sampling bug?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What would you build for your local market first? Let me know on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/Jilyac&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://discord.gg/syvRUScU&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Discord&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AskPoker.ai Log #1: Reality Check and Pivot to Concierge MVP</title>
      <link>/devlog/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/devlog/1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;askpokerai-week-1-reality-check-and-pivot-to-concierge-mvp&#34;&gt;AskPoker.ai Week 1: Reality Check and Pivot to Concierge MVP&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I learned some hard truths about my assumptions building 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.askpoker.ai/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AskPoker.ai&lt;/a&gt;. Time for radical honesty about what&amp;rsquo;s working and what isn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For context, AskPoker.ai is my attempt to build a conversational AI poker coach that gives recreational players instant, solver-backed analysis of their hands. Instead of wrestling with complex software like PioSOLVER, players can just describe their hand in plain English and get clear strategic advice. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on this for about 6 months, and this is my first public update on the journey. You can read more about the original vision in my 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jiliac.com/post/askpoker/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;announcement post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-tried-forum-engagement-experiment&#34;&gt;What I Tried: Forum Engagement Experiment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My plan was simple: test demand by answering poker hands on Reddit and 2+2 with AskPoker analysis. Use the tool to generate insights, then sign responses with &amp;ldquo;made with askpoker.ai&amp;rdquo; to see if people were interested in the platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal was to validate the core value proposition while driving some early traffic. What I found instead was a masterclass in why assumptions need real-world testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hard-truths-discovered&#34;&gt;Hard Truths Discovered&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-the-product-isnt-ready&#34;&gt;1. The Product Isn&amp;rsquo;t Ready&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table size limitation&lt;/strong&gt;: My backend solver only handles 5-max tables, not the 6+ player tables common in most online games. When users post hands from full ring games, the solver has no data, so the LLM just improvises answers based on general poker knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew this was a constraint going in, but experiencing it in practice hit different. I now understand I &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; solve this limitation eventually (though interestingly, in the French market where 5-max cash games dominate, this might not be as critical).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scope mismatch&lt;/strong&gt;: I built the tool to analyze single decisions (&amp;ldquo;Should I call this river bet?&amp;quot;), but users want comprehensive hand reviews. They want to know where their decisions went wrong across multiple streets, not just get advice on one spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insufficient backend data&lt;/strong&gt;: The solver gives me the optimal action, but lacks the rich context needed for proper explanations - full ranges, equity calculations, expected value, fold equity. Without this data, the LLM fills in gaps with educated guesses that sometimes sound confident but are wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Basic bugs&lt;/strong&gt;: Simple things like currency-to-blind conversion. I expected the LLM to handle this automatically when calling the backend, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-market-reality-check&#34;&gt;2. Market Reality Check&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forum fragmentation&lt;/strong&gt;: Even active communities like 2+2 and Reddit aren&amp;rsquo;t exactly buzzing with activity. There&amp;rsquo;s discussion, but it&amp;rsquo;s not the vibrant marketplace of poker questions I had imagined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;French market gap&lt;/strong&gt;: I found essentially no active French poker discussion platforms. This surprised me - I expected at least some local communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User behavior insight&lt;/strong&gt;: Players consume more content (YouTube, training sites) than they engage in forum discussions. This suggests my marketing approach needs to meet users where they actually spend time, not where I assumed they&amp;rsquo;d be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-the-concierge-mvp-reality-check&#34;&gt;3. The Concierge MVP Reality Check&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s where brutal honesty matters: my initial assessment was too rosy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Actual results&lt;/strong&gt;: About 75% of my responses were ignored, ~15% got genuine positive responses from users (actual replies thanking me for the analysis), and ~10% were called out for containing errors where the LLM had hallucinated explanations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reddit truth&lt;/strong&gt;: People might not always give positive feedback when you help them, but they &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; let wrong analysis slide. Every mistake gets caught and corrected, often harshly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key insight&lt;/strong&gt;: Demand absolutely exists for expert-level analysis in accessible language, but the quality bar is unforgiving. There&amp;rsquo;s no room for &amp;ldquo;pretty good&amp;rdquo; when giving strategic advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-pivot-from-product-to-process&#34;&gt;The Pivot: From Product to Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-concierge-mvp-makes-sense&#34;&gt;Why Concierge MVP Makes Sense&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The product is too broken for self-service user testing, but the manual approach validates something crucial: the core value proposition works when executed correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More importantly, I need to answer a fundamental question: &lt;strong&gt;Are recreational players ready to trust an AI coach?&lt;/strong&gt; This is about more than just technical capability - it&amp;rsquo;s about user psychology and market readiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I&amp;rsquo;m confident I can solve the technical issues given enough time, creating trust is a different challenge entirely. This requires marketing and communication skills that aren&amp;rsquo;t in my natural wheelhouse, making validation even more critical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My new process: users message me via email or Discord for hand analysis. I use the backend tool to generate insights, then manually refine and explain the analysis. This creates a controlled environment to test whether players accept AI-driven coaching when it&amp;rsquo;s delivered thoughtfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;new-strategy-content-led-growth&#34;&gt;New Strategy: Content-Led Growth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blog foundation&lt;/strong&gt;: Generate poker-specific content using the LLM+solver combination. This content becomes source material for TikTok scripts and other marketing efforts - creating a scalable content system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TikTok expansion&lt;/strong&gt;: Meet users where they actually are, not in forums. Poker content performs well on TikTok, and the format suits quick hand analysis and strategy tips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Novel LLM usage&lt;/strong&gt;: This isn&amp;rsquo;t just automating existing tasks - I&amp;rsquo;m using AI as both an exploration agent (to probe solver outputs) and as a writer (to explain complex concepts clearly). This combination creates content capabilities that didn&amp;rsquo;t exist before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transparent AI positioning&lt;/strong&gt;: Brand myself as &amp;ldquo;Human + AI&amp;rdquo; poker analysis. Be upfront about using AI tools while emphasizing human judgment and experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;technical-priorities-despite-no-product-development&#34;&gt;Technical Priorities (Despite &amp;ldquo;No Product Development&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said I&amp;rsquo;d stop building features, but I need to fix the solver-LLM pipeline to eliminate hallucinations. The focus shifts from user-facing features to content creation tools:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix solver data output to provide complete strategic context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build reliable solver-LLM pipeline for scalable content creation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop the infrastructure needed for consistent, accurate analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;whats-next&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s Next&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weekly devlogs&lt;/strong&gt;: Continue documenting discoveries and pivots transparently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manual hand analysis&lt;/strong&gt;: Build audience and expertise through direct engagement while testing AI coach acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content system development&lt;/strong&gt;: Create the infrastructure for scalable marketing through AI-assisted content creation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eventual transition&lt;/strong&gt;: Move from concierge to automated product once the core experience is proven and technical limitations are resolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;closing-reflection&#34;&gt;Closing Reflection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the best product development is realizing when to stop developing and start validating. This week taught me that building in public means being honest about failures, not just successes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The forum experiment didn&amp;rsquo;t go as planned, but it revealed something more valuable than validation: it showed me exactly what needs to be fixed and where my assumptions were wrong. That&amp;rsquo;s worth more than a hundred positive feedback comments on a fundamentally flawed approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next week: Testing how far I can push the LLM+solver integration to create a scalable marketing system. Building out the new website with proper landing page and CMS, then seeing what kind of poker content I can generate automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Try the conversational expertise approach yourself at 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://chat.askpoker.ai&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;askpoker.ai&lt;/a&gt;, or contact me on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://discord.gg/syvRUScU&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Discord&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Everyone&#39;s Missing the Real GPT Opportunity (And How I&#39;m Building It)</title>
      <link>/post/askpoker/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/askpoker/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Everyone&amp;rsquo;s building ChatGPT wrappers. But they&amp;rsquo;re missing the real opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-great-misunderstanding&#34;&gt;The Great Misunderstanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone&amp;rsquo;s building ChatGPT wrappers. Scroll through Product Hunt or Y Combinator&amp;rsquo;s latest batch and you&amp;rsquo;ll see the pattern: database queries become &amp;lsquo;natural language analytics,&amp;rsquo; search engines get chat interfaces, productivity tools gain conversational layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s 2007 all over again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the iPhone launched, most people thought &amp;ldquo;it&amp;rsquo;s just a better phone with internet.&amp;rdquo; They completely missed that we were about to see entirely new application categories emerge—Uber, Instagram, Tinder. Apps that couldn&amp;rsquo;t exist before the smartphone, not because the technology wasn&amp;rsquo;t ready, but because the interaction paradigm wasn&amp;rsquo;t there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, we&amp;rsquo;re making the same mistake with LLMs (Large Language Models). We&amp;rsquo;re thinking too small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-llms-actually-enable&#34;&gt;What LLMs Actually Enable&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real opportunity isn&amp;rsquo;t making existing tools more conversational. It&amp;rsquo;s creating entirely new experiences that were never economically viable before:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personalized expertise at scale:&lt;/strong&gt; AI that adapts to individual knowledge gaps and communication styles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context-aware coaching:&lt;/strong&gt; Understanding not just what you&amp;rsquo;re asking, but why you&amp;rsquo;re confused&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real-time learning:&lt;/strong&gt; Immediate feedback loops for complex decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pattern to look for isn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;how do we make X more accessible?&amp;rdquo; It&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;what expertise bottlenecks can we eliminate entirely?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-case-study-in-missing-the-point&#34;&gt;A Case Study in Missing the Point&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me show you what I mean with poker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professional poker players use tools called &amp;ldquo;solvers&amp;rdquo;—sophisticated algorithms that calculate mathematically optimal strategy. Think of them as the chess engines of poker. Tools like PioSOLVER and GTO Wizard can tell you the perfect play in any situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they&amp;rsquo;re designed for experts. The interfaces look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;Complex solver interface with ranges, frequencies, and technical data that&#39;s overwhelming for beginners&#34;
    src=&#34;/img/gto_wiz.jpg&#34; width=&#34;600px&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monthly subscriptions run €100+. Setup requires technical knowledge. The learning curve is brutal. One forum user described trying to learn PioSOLVER as &amp;ldquo;requiring a fair amount of technical knowledge&amp;hellip; for a lot of players, it was a frustrating experience.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-obvious-wrong-solution&#34;&gt;The Obvious (Wrong) Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people would see this and think: &amp;ldquo;Just put a chat interface on top of the solver!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take GTO Wizard&amp;rsquo;s complex output, add a conversational wrapper, maybe simplify the display a bit. Same underlying complexity, slightly friendlier packaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is exactly the kind of &amp;ldquo;AI wrapper&amp;rdquo; thinking that misses the real opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-real-opportunity-entirely-new-experiences&#34;&gt;The Real Opportunity: Entirely New Experiences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of asking &amp;ldquo;how do we make solvers easier to use?&amp;rdquo; I asked &amp;ldquo;what coaching experiences were never possible before?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That led me to build 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://askpoker.ai&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;AskPoker.ai&lt;/a&gt;. Here&amp;rsquo;s what a session looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;I raised pocket nines from middle position, got called by button and big blind. Flop came A-9-5 rainbow. I bet, button folded, big blind raised. Should I call or re-raise?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AskPoker:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;You have a monster hand with middle set on this board. The BB&amp;rsquo;s min-raise could be a weaker ace trying to build the pot, two pair like A5 or A9, a draw like 67 or 78, or even a pure bluff with missed hands. Raising is better than calling for several key reasons&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t a better interface for existing tools. It&amp;rsquo;s a fundamentally new interaction that bridges expert algorithms with human communication patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-this-works&#34;&gt;Why This Works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The magic happens in the gap between computational power and human understanding:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Natural expression:&lt;/strong&gt; Describe hands like talking to a friend, not inputting technical parameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instant expertise:&lt;/strong&gt; Get solver-backed analysis without learning complex software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contextual explanations:&lt;/strong&gt; AI adapts explanations to your level and explains the &amp;ldquo;why&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Immediate feedback:&lt;/strong&gt; Review confusing hands right after they happen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early validation is promising. When I manually provide this kind of analysis on poker forums, users specifically thank me while ignoring other responses in the same threads. There&amp;rsquo;s real demand for this bridge between expert knowledge and accessible communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bigger-pattern&#34;&gt;The Bigger Pattern&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poker is just one example. The pattern applies anywhere you find:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complex domains&lt;/strong&gt; where expertise is expensive and hard to access&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High-context decisions&lt;/strong&gt; where generic advice isn&amp;rsquo;t enough&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning-oriented users&lt;/strong&gt; who want to understand, not just get answers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think legal strategy coaching for small firms. Medical decision support for patients navigating treatment options. Business strategy guidance for specific competitive situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aren&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;better interfaces for existing tools.&amp;rdquo; They&amp;rsquo;re entirely new coaching experiences that eliminate expertise bottlenecks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-window-wont-stay-open&#34;&gt;The Window Won&amp;rsquo;t Stay Open&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re still early. Most LLM applications remain glorified chatbots for existing workflows. But that&amp;rsquo;s changing fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first movers who identify these expertise gaps and build new experiences around them will establish category-defining positions. Just like Uber didn&amp;rsquo;t win by making taxi companies more efficient—they eliminated the taxi bottleneck entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional solver companies face an innovator&amp;rsquo;s dilemma. Adding conversational AI would cannibalize their complex, high-priced products. But someone will build these bridges between expert systems and human understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-this-means-for-you&#34;&gt;What This Means for You&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The smartphone moment for LLMs isn&amp;rsquo;t about making everything conversational. It&amp;rsquo;s about enabling entirely new experiences that were never economically viable before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for expertise bottlenecks in domains you know well. Where do people struggle to access or apply complex knowledge? Where are the gaps between what algorithms can compute and what humans can understand?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those gaps are where the next generation of applications will emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Try the conversational expertise approach yourself at 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://chat.askpoker.ai&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;askpoker.ai&lt;/a&gt;, or join our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://discord.gg/syvRUScU&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Discord&lt;/a&gt; to explore similar opportunities in your domain. The real LLM revolution is just getting started.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Blockchain will Replace your Backend</title>
      <link>/post/blockchain-backend/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/blockchain-backend/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What if we could stop wasting most of our development time re-developing the same thing again and again?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feeling I got whenever starting a new hobby project is that before getting to the meat and having fun, I had to spend a significant amount of time doing trivial stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my latest hobby project, I discovered there was an area where developers stopped wasting their time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, a new project starts like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create front and basic API&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a quick docker-compose for ease of development (maybe)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a local DB, connect your backend to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probably you have users, so setup authentication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get to the meat of your project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time I get to (5), I lost excitement. On my last project though, it felt different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the title gave away, this project was in the (so-called) web 3 space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fast-dev&#34;&gt;🍔 Fast Dev&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally I had a lot of misgivings about the area. What can you do with a blockchain that you can’t do with a database? What value does it bring?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IMO there is a 70% chance that this whole web 3 thing will be a flop. But if the other 30% comes to happen, it will be big. So it’s 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jiliac.com/post/cryptoskeptic/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;worth investing&lt;/a&gt; time to learn how it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So off I went on this first learning project. (Live at 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://invisoo.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;invisoo.com&lt;/a&gt;. I’ll write another blog to talk more about the project and its design decisions.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what starting this project looked like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create basic front and smart contract&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dockerize&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get to the meat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First shortcut: a contract can serve as both your backend and your DB (i.e. execution and storage). You don’t need to deal with authentication because web 3 users come with an identity in the form of their wallet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;piece-of-the-whole&#34;&gt;🍕Piece of the Whole&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout my development, I got the feeling of being able to leverage of “bigger whole”. It starts with user/wallet handling but it goes on&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I felt the inter-connected of web 3 shined by how ubiquitous tokens are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.openzeppelin.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Open Zeppelin&lt;/a&gt; you can easily customize a token implementation to your needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;500px&#34; src=&#34;/img/blockchain-backend/open-zeppelin.png&#34;
alt=&#34;Open Zeppelin Token Wizard&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New tokens are supported by every wallet without any need for you to do anything.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://etherscan.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Online transaction explorers&lt;/a&gt; will detect underlying token transfers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;600px&#34; src=&#34;/img/blockchain-backend/scan.png&#34;
alt=&#34;A Full Reveal from PolygonScan&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using tokens make your DApp “pluggable” into an even bigger part of the ecosystem. For example, once you transfer a token to the user, he can use it with any other DApp. For example, he could go and trade it at 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://uniswap.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Uniswap&lt;/a&gt; even though trading wasn’t in your original design.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Tokens may not be your go-to design though. I also didn’t consider them at the beginning. I’ll expand on why I modified the design of my project to use tokens in the next blog. I found the implementation easier this way.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To expand on the third point, I found online transaction explorers mind-blowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You just deploy, you don’t have to do anything and you can visualize every interaction of a user with your contract. This is the benefit of operating on a transparent data layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can easily see the current state of your contract, the users and also all the historical transactions that brought us to this state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-less-fun&#34;&gt;🥦 The Less Fun&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing I found buggy is the handling of chains. Which chain is the user connected to? The localhost chain? The test chain? The main chain (i.e. Ethereum).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the chain the user is connected to, we need to rely on a different “provider”. The provider allows our front to read and write the blockchain. It’s sad that we have to rely on a centralized intermediary, but it’s necessary in a world where users don’t run and index the blockchain locally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another pain I felt while developing is doing math. By default smart contracts only handle integers. In the end, you can just import some library to solve this problem but it’s still messy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m still not sure what value Web 3 brings to the users, but at least I found it does bring value to developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problems are small compared to the value provided by being part of a big ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operating on a transparent data layer like the blockchain will not fit every design though. All data has to be public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web 3 people would say that’s not a bug but a feature 😛&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World to Verifiable Credentials</title>
      <link>/post/vc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/vc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-this-is-about&#34;&gt;What this is about&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a basic programming showcase of VCs (read on to know what they are).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code can be found on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Jiliac/verifiable-credential/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; but I&amp;rsquo;ll share the most important snippet here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-vcs-what&#34;&gt;🤯 VCs what?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verifiable credentials (VCs) are the translation of physical credentials like a driving license or a degree in the digital world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relying on cryptographic proofs enables several advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impossible to fake&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scalable since digital (for all the actor involved)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enables minimum disclosure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last point may be fuzzy because we never do it in the physical world. Let’s take an example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you are asked to prove you are an adult. By showing your ID, you actually reveal much more than a binary “I’m an adult” or “I’m an minor”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You reveal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your exact age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-whos-playing&#34;&gt;🕹️ Who’s playing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three roles involve with any type of credential:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Issuer&lt;/strong&gt;: creation of the credential&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Subject&lt;/strong&gt;: The credential is about them. They receive it, hold it and share it with the Verifiers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Verifier&lt;/strong&gt;: Receive and verify the proofs from Subjects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;The Three Roles concerning Credentials&#34;
    src=&#34;/img/vc/three_roles.png&#34; width=&#34;600px&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s take a close (technical 🤓) look at each of the role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;part-i-the-issuance&#34;&gt;Part I: The Issuance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say the issuer is my university. I just graduated and I get issued a degree:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;{
  &amp;quot;age&amp;quot;: 24,
  &amp;quot;universityName&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Oxford&amp;quot;,
  &amp;quot;degree&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Bachelor of Science&amp;quot;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above is the &lt;em&gt;claim&lt;/em&gt; of the credential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;The Three Parts of a Verifiable Credential&#34;
    src=&#34;/img/vc/credential_parts.png&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our next goal is to get the issuer to &lt;em&gt;sign&lt;/em&gt; this claim. This signature will be the proof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do so, the issuer needs two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To have a digital presence. Which is represented cryptographically by a public and private key.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To know &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt; is the subject. In digital terms, what’s the public key of the &lt;em&gt;subject&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;type KeyPair struct {
	PublicKey  ed25519.PublicKey
	PrivateKey ed25519.PrivateKey
}

type Issuer struct {
	keys KeyPair

	ID   string
	Name string
}

type Subject struct {
	keys KeyPair
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is enough to get our first verifiable credential signed 🚀&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An issuer, meaning a public and a private key&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The public key of the subject. (Below this is the &lt;code&gt;subjectID&lt;/code&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A claim&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;func (i Issuer) SignCredential(claim Claim, subjectID []byte) (Credential, error) {
	creds := Credential{
		Context:          vcContext,
		TypeOfCredential: append(claim.GetType(), vcType),
		Issuer:           i,
		IssuanceDate:     time.Now(),
		CredentialSubject: CredentialSubject{
			ID:    subjectID,
			Claim: claim,
		},
	}

	creds.Proof = SignProof(i.keys, creds.ToBytes())
	return creds, err
}

func SignProof(keys KeyPair, docToSign) Proof {
	proof := Proof{
		TypeOfProof: ed25519Type,
		Created:     time.Now(),
		Creator:     keys.PublicKey,
	}

	proof.Signature = ed25519.Sign(keys.PrivateKey, docToSign)

	return proof
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The output would look like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;{
  &amp;quot;context&amp;quot;: [   
    &amp;quot;https://www.w3.org/2018/credentials/v1&amp;quot;
  ], 
  &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: [    
    &amp;quot;GraduationCredential&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;VerifiableCredential&amp;quot;   
  ],  
  &amp;quot;issuer&amp;quot;: {     
    &amp;quot;ID&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;https://oxford.com/issuers/1&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;Name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;The Marvelous University of Oxford&amp;quot;           
  },   
  &amp;quot;issuanceDate&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;2022-01-11T16:49:46.424839+01:00&amp;quot;,
  &amp;quot;credentialSubject&amp;quot;: {          
    &amp;quot;id&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;CmwdBhPLKTvX8EeaUFnRsHJ/UXspbvU4o3DDPnRK8Ws=&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;claim&amp;quot;: {
      &amp;quot;age&amp;quot;: 24,
      &amp;quot;universityName&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Oxford&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;degree&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Bachelor of Science&amp;quot;
    }
  },
  &amp;quot;proof&amp;quot;: {
    &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Ed25519Signature2018&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;created&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;2022-01-11T16:49:46.425012+01:00&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;creator&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;i+HjQgi8ln5OEXuFKtaW0A1LwJo6o95tcKv+dtGFw/I=&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;signature&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;P0HOyLzkYD65KPxLrKF0jHzuLkhzHGFj1+6MnEa9329uaE88v0Pp1uB7KR+SONwE5pBq6ZMGgfwScWb0SIQ5Dg==&amp;quot;
  }   
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;context&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;type&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;issuanceDate&lt;/code&gt; are the metadata of the VC. They will usually be present in all VCs but for our first understanding of their usage, we can ignore them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this example, I’ve chosen to put the public keys directly in the VC. The &lt;code&gt;proof.creator&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;credentialSubject.id&lt;/code&gt; fields are respectively the public keys of the issuer and the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a real application, they would be a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decentralized_identifier&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Decentralized Identifier&lt;/a&gt; (DID) which would point to the keys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A DID can resolve to multiple public keys&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A DID enable the rotation of these keys&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A DID can resolve to service endpoints&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: If you look at 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Jiliac/verifiable-credential&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the full code in the repo&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll see that in the excerpt above I cheated twice 😛. I hope you’ll forgive these simplifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;part-ii-the-presentation-by-the-subject&#34;&gt;Part II: The Presentation (by the Subject)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
  &lt;img alt=&#34;The Three Roles concerning Credentials&#34;
    src=&#34;/img/vc/three_roles.png&#34; width=&#34;600px&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that our subject has its degree, he can present it to an employer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may be thinking: well, in the real world, I just show my credential to the verifier and that’s it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except, there is this moment when you give your driving license to a police officer where he checks that your face looks like the photo on your ID. What is this check for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Found it? It’s to check that you are the real owner of the credential. The police officer wants to make sure you didn’t happen to give him a credential about someone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does this step translate in the digital world?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s what we call the &lt;strong&gt;Presentation&lt;/strong&gt; of the credential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To make sure the subject presents a credential that is his, the verifier asks him to sign the credential.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may think: we are coming back to the same problem. The subject could steal an old presentation and give it to the verifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s why the verifier provides a “challenge” to the subject to include in its presentation. It ensures the presentation was done by the subject just for this verification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This challenge is called a &lt;em&gt;nonce&lt;/em&gt; (i.e. a number only used once).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fuzzy? Let’s get in the code to make it clearer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;func main() {
	// ...

	nonce := verifier.MakeNonce()
	presentation, err := subject.SignPresentation(credentials, nonce)
}

func (s Subject) SignPresentation(credentials Credential, nonce []byte) (
	Presentation, error) {

	presentation := Presentation{
		Context:            vcContext,
		TypeOfPresentation: []string{presType},
		Credential:         credentials,
		Nonce:              nonce,
	}

	presentation.Proof = SignProof(s.keys, presentation.ToBytes())
	return presentation, err
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presentation we get as output:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;{      
  &amp;quot;context&amp;quot;: [   
    &amp;quot;https://www.w3.org/2018/credentials/v1&amp;quot;  
  ],
  &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: [ 
    &amp;quot;VerifiablePresentation&amp;quot;     
  ],
  &amp;quot;credential&amp;quot;: {
    &amp;quot;context&amp;quot;: [
      &amp;quot;https://www.w3.org/2018/credentials/v1&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: [
      &amp;quot;GraduationCredential&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;VerifiableCredential&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;issuer&amp;quot;: {
      &amp;quot;ID&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;https://oxford.com/issuers/1&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;Name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;The Marvelous University of Oxford&amp;quot;
    },
    &amp;quot;issuanceDate&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;2022-01-11T16:49:46.424839+01:00&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;credentialSubject&amp;quot;: {
      &amp;quot;id&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;CmwdBhPLKTvX8EeaUFnRsHJ/UXspbvU4o3DDPnRK8Ws=&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;claim&amp;quot;: {
        &amp;quot;age&amp;quot;: 24,
        &amp;quot;universityName&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Oxford&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;degree&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Bachelor of Science&amp;quot;
      }
    },
    &amp;quot;proof&amp;quot;: {
      &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Ed25519Signature2018&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;created&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;2022-01-11T16:49:46.425012+01:00&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;creator&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;i+HjQgi8ln5OEXuFKtaW0A1LwJo6o95tcKv+dtGFw/I=&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;signature&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;P0HOyLzkYD65KPxLrKF0jHzuLkhzHGFj1+6MnEa9329uaE88v0Pp1uB7KR+SONwE5pBq6ZMGgfwScWb0SIQ5Dg==&amp;quot;
    }
  },
  &amp;quot;nonce&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Uv38ByGCZU8WP18P&amp;quot;,
  &amp;quot;proof&amp;quot;: {
    &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Ed25519Signature2018&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;created&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;2022-01-11T16:49:46.425128+01:00&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;creator&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;CmwdBhPLKTvX8EeaUFnRsHJ/UXspbvU4o3DDPnRK8Ws=&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;signature&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;raseJvdviujKjsDGCV9A+K7o4zaMW2rqGpihXZKBqNdQvNhFgWnA5jsc1wjJ4ZQdC7I/GBRA9NBzAm7EwIT2Ag==&amp;quot;
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;part-iii-the-verification&#34;&gt;Part III: The Verification&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The verifier has three things to check in the presentation above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The proof is signed by the subject of the credential (and the nonce is correct).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The credential is correctly signed by the issuer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The presentation is correctly signed by the subject.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first check is easily done: Are the &lt;code&gt;proof.created&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;credential.credentialSubject.id&lt;/code&gt; equal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two others verifies that the signature matches the public key and the content the proof is about (the credential or the presentation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34;&gt;func verifiesSignature(proof Proof, signedDoc []byte) bool {
	pubKey := proof.Creator
	signature := proof.Signature

	return ed25519.Verify(pubKey, signedDoc, signature)
}

func (v Verifier) VerifiesPresentation(presentation Presentation) (err error) {
	// 1 - Checks the Presentation is signed by the Subject of the credential
	credential := presentation.Credential
	credentialSubjectID := credential.CredentialSubject.ID
	presentationProver := presentation.Proof.Creator
	if bytes.Compare(credentialSubjectID, presentationProver) != 0 {
		return fmt.Errorf(&amp;quot;Presentation prover is not the credential subject.&amp;quot;)
	}

	// 2 - Checks the credential
	okCred := verifiesSignature(credential.Proof, credential.ToBytes())
	if !okCred {
		return fmt.Errorf(&amp;quot;Invalid credential signature.&amp;quot;)
	}

	// 3 - Checks the presentation
	okPres := verifiesSignature(presentation.Proof, presentation.ToBytes())
	if !okPres {
		return fmt.Errorf(&amp;quot;Invalid presentation signature.&amp;quot;)
	}

	return err
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“VCs are just signed JSON.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although they are new, obscure and not currently common aren’t so scary once you get to play them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope this was useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Valentin, signing off 🖋️&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conversion of a Crypto-Skeptic</title>
      <link>/post/cryptoskeptic/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/cryptoskeptic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Look inside: What’s the promise of the blockchain you believe in? That it will change the world? Or that it will make you rich?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are not the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin is the first internet-native way to speculate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technology could become omnipresent while the first crypto-currency becomes irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To succeed a technology needs more than a vertical chart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;600px&#34; src=&#34;/img/cryptoskeptic/bitcoin_price.png&#34;
alt=&#34;Bitcoin to the moon!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To drive widespread adoption, a technology needs to be useful, to solve a problem.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A car has a clear benefit. You move. Fast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steam enabled mechanization of production.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With internet I can communicate with anyone, anywhere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can I do with a Bitcoin?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first heard of the blockchain in 2013. Until this summer (2021), I didn’t believe it had any chance of becoming useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Siding out central banks may be exciting for hard core libertarian. But it’s not going to cut it for most people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The true reason 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.binance.com/en/blog/markets/the-world-goes-crypto-top-5-countries-adopting-crypto-and-how-busd-helps-421499824684902531&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;300 millions people invested in cryptos&lt;/a&gt; isn’t the ideology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s the quick buck&lt;/strong&gt; 💸&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one can deny that Bitcoin failed on its initial promise. It did not become a “coin”, an internet-native currency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As all good marketers do, the fanboys changed the claim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Oh it was never about making a currency. Bitcoin is a store of value. An internet-native gold.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except gold doesn’t lose 50% of its value every other week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;600px&#34; src=&#34;/img/cryptoskeptic/bitcoin_gold.png&#34;
alt=&#34;Gold vs Bitcoin&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Source: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://aswathdamodaran.blogspot.com/2020/11/a-viral-market-update-xiv-wrap-on-covid.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Aswath Damodaran&lt;/a&gt;. Bitcoin didn’t achieve gold stability.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tipping-point&#34;&gt;⛰️ The Tipping Point&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still. All the media noise around 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-fungible_token&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NFTs&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Web3&lt;/a&gt; tipped me over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After looking into it, I finally believed there may be something to this chain of block thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s so special about it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with NFTs and come back to Web3 later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, you could say NFTs just pulled the same trick as crypto-currencies: Being another channel for rollercoaster speculation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let’s go deeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NFTs have the potential to support the creator economy (artists, writers, podcasters, youtubers&amp;hellip;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And more than enabling the purchase of their creation, an &lt;strong&gt;NFT could give its holder &lt;em&gt;rights&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where Bitcoin is blocked into being a commodity, NFTs have unlimited flexibility in the rights they can give.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An NFT could represent the right to meet its creator in 1-1s, or the right to attend his events (i.e., tickets), or the right to vote/participate in the next creation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I admit it is still fuzzy what the ownership of an NFT could represent, but this flexibility opens the door to USEFULNESS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sorare&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sorare&lt;/a&gt; uses NFTs to create a collectible card game where cards are tradeable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bubble-economy&#34;&gt;🎈 Bubble Economy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment, the area is awash with capital. All sorts of projects get funded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at any of the major technology developments in the past, there has always been a &lt;em&gt;frenzy&lt;/em&gt; of funding at first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be it in the steam age, the railways, or in IT, at the start, there is a bubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;600px&#34; src=&#34;/img/cryptoskeptic/new_tech_frenzy.png&#34;
alt=&#34;Frenzy of new technology&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(From “Technological Revolution and Financial Capital” by Carlota Perez.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dawn of AI was predicted in the 1970s but only happened in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://tim.blog/2021/10/28/chris-dixon-naval-ravikant/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Even crypto experts&lt;/a&gt; agree there is no doubt there is a bubble around crypto-assets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People telling you with 100% certainty that blockchain is the future are lying. Either to you or to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can only be certain of the blockchain usefulness once it is widely adopted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, we are at the start and we can only hope to catch a glimpse of the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;/rant_end&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-glimpse&#34;&gt;👀 The Glimpse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NFTs were the appetizer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s the main course that converted me: Web3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;”Web3 is the internet owned by the builders and users, orchestrated with tokens.”&lt;/em&gt; — Chris Dixon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the magic happens at the “orchestrated with token”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orchestrated means governed or administrated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A token is a right. (As with NFTs, since they are also token, only non-fungible.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blurry. But this opens the door for a new kind of social organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now this takes the form of 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hackernoon.com/what-is-a-dao-c7e84aa1bd69&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Decentralized Autonomous Organizations&lt;/a&gt; (DAO)
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hackernoon.com/what-is-a-dao-c7e84aa1bd69&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, last November, ConstitutionDAO was formed in a few days to buy one of the 13 original United States Constitution copies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They raised $43 millions from 17,437 contributors in 72h.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Kickstarter could have done the same, no?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have the technology to do so. But a single project never even raised half this amount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TRUST.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;”Trust minimization is reducing the vulnerability of participants to each other’s and to outsiders’ and intermediaries potential for harmful behavior.”&lt;/em&gt; — 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://unenumerated.blogspot.com/2017/02/money-blockchains-and-social-scalability.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nick Szabo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the beginning the main strength of the protocol invented by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satoshi_Nakamoto&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Satoshi Nakamoto&lt;/a&gt; is the little to no trust you need to have trust in the other participants to engage with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to trust the people, the group or its leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You just need to trust the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my life I signed 1000s of contracts which I didn’t read. Because the contracts are just an insurance for worst case scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In truth, when you sign a contract you trust the people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smart_contract&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;smart contract&lt;/a&gt; on the blockchain, it’s different. It defines the mode of interaction with this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The members of ConstitutionDAO knew their money could only be used to buy the constitution. They knew they’d be able to vote on what would be done with it afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seller, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sotheby%27s&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sotheby’s&lt;/a&gt;, knew it could trust this organization (which didn’t exist the week before) to afford its bid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike usual contracts, you don’t even need to trust the State to enforce your contract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The smart contract self-enforce. You don’t need to do anything for it to execute (and you couldn’t stop it if you wanted to).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the real world, contracts are never self-enforced. You need lawyers. Which are&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not free. Both in terms of money and time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time is key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-humans-do-best&#34;&gt;👬 What Humans Do Best&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do humans dominate all other species?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our cognitive capacity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may be ever so smart. But alone you are nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The key difference: We are social. We make groups and coordinate.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These groups grow to towns, cities and nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Why_Nations_Fail&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;“Why Nations Fail?”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their book, Acemoglu and Robinson have a clear answer: Because nations don’t have &lt;em&gt;inclusive&lt;/em&gt; enough institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are not able to participate in their own governance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not an article about democracy so I won’t expand much longer on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All our democracies and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_contract&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;our social contracts&lt;/a&gt; did not evolve for nearly a century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law is too slow, too costly. We have a single vote between two different options every other year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world is too complex for this to be enough. We need a new way to interact with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To take group decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding new modes of social organization is an even more important challenge than surviving climate change in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I think the blockchain is the technology that can enable the &lt;em&gt;social innovations&lt;/em&gt; we need to level up human organizations.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast experiments are the enabler of discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blockchain is the technology unlocking this speed by lowering the trust requirement for social organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know this is only a glimpse 🔭&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it’s enough to get me excited in the field and speculate on its success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I speculate with the most valuable resource I have: time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Strong opinions, loosely held.”&lt;/em&gt; — Marc Andreessen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you disagree with any of the above, send me a mail at 
&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:valentinmanes@outlook.fr&#34;&gt;valentinmanes@outlook.fr&lt;/a&gt; to enrich our ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, if you have a favorite resource you think I should start with, I’ll gladly take any advice since the area is so wide and a bit overwhelming to enter in.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trop débordé pour un mouton ? Alors ce n&#39;est pas pour vous</title>
      <link>/post/petit_prince/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/petit_prince/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ça fait 18 mois que je travaille sur ce projet. J&amp;rsquo;ai misé toute ma carrière dessus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Je suis dans la dernière ligne droite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma femme me dérange avec des histoires de réservation d’hôtel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🧨 J&amp;rsquo;explose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elle ne voit pas que ce projet est primordial ? Que je n&amp;rsquo;ai pas le temps pour ce genre de détail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;400px&#34; src=&#34;/img/petit_prince/rose.jpeg&#34;
alt=&#34;une rose qui pique&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Les épines, à quoi servent-elles ?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le petit prince ne renonce jamais à une question. J’étais irrité par mon boulon et je répondis n&amp;rsquo;importe quoi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;400px&#34; src=&#34;/img/petit_prince/petit_prince_book.jpeg&#34;
alt=&#34;Le Petit Prince (couverture)&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C&amp;rsquo;est ce comportement que dénonce Saint-Exupéry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le cerveau humain est une machine à créer (et résoudre) des problèmes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On croit qu&amp;rsquo;une fois que l&amp;rsquo;on aura LE problème en face de nous, notre vie sera le paradis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Si seulement j&amp;rsquo;avais la solution&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mauvaise nouvelle : Le monde ne peut pas être parfait. Il y aura toujours une imperfection à corriger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Tout le malheur des hommes vient de ne savoir pas demeurer en repos, dans une chambre.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; — Blaise Pascal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Si je regarde mon problème de plus près, il ne fait plus beaucoup de sens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;À quoi cela te sert-il de posséder les étoiles ?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ça me sert à être riche.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Et à quoi cela te sert-il d’être riche ?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;À acheter d&amp;rsquo;autres étoiles.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Celui-là, se dit en lui-même le petit prince, il raisonne un peu comme mon ivrogne.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-le-bonheur-juste-là&#34;&gt;🙋 Le Bonheur, Juste Là&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le Petit Prince, ce n&amp;rsquo;est pas juste un livre critique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La solution nous vient de monsieur le renard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;600px&#34; src=&#34;/img/petit_prince/renard.jpeg&#34;
alt=&#34;La sagesse du Renard&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Les hommes n&amp;rsquo;ont plus le temps de rien connaître. Ils achètent des choses toutes faites chez les marchands. Mais comme il n&amp;rsquo;existe point de marchands d&amp;rsquo;amis, les hommes n&amp;rsquo;ont plus d&amp;rsquo;amis. Si tu veux un ami, apprivoise-moi !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La générosité, la gratitude, l&amp;rsquo;amour. Prendre le temps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La pénurie de 2021, ce n&amp;rsquo;est pas le gazole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encore plus aujourd&amp;rsquo;hui qu’à l’époque de Saint-Exupéry, ce qui nous manque c&amp;rsquo;est plus d’appréciation pour ce que nous avons déjà.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peu importe les problèmes de notre quotidien. Si nous avons quelqu&amp;rsquo;un à chérir, nous avons tout ce qu&amp;rsquo;il nous faut pour être heureux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On ne voit bien qu&amp;rsquo;avec le cœur. L&amp;rsquo;essentiel est invisible pour les yeux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le savoir c&amp;rsquo;est une chose. Mais quand je vois comment j&amp;rsquo;ai réagi avec ma femme, clairement ce n&amp;rsquo;est pas assez.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L&amp;rsquo;amour se pratique.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quotidiennement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bien à propos, ma cousine m&amp;rsquo;a envoyé un &amp;ldquo;calendrier de l&amp;rsquo;avent de bienveillance&amp;rdquo;. Parfait pour une première mise en pratique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;600px&#34; src=&#34;/img/petit_prince/avent.jpeg&#34;
alt=&#34;Pratiquer l&#39;Amour Tous les Jours&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Valentin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PS&lt;/strong&gt; : L&amp;rsquo;amour se partage. Alors envoyez cet article à vos amis 🤲&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pour recevoir plus de sagesse du Petit Prince par mail, inscrivez-vous à

&lt;a href=&#34;https://mimima.fr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;mimima.fr&lt;/a&gt; (si vous n’êtes pas déjà inscrit).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ankou: Painful Creativity</title>
      <link>/post/ankou_creativity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/ankou_creativity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you want to increase your success rate, double your failure rate.”
&lt;em&gt;Thomas J. Watson, IBM CEO&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not said enough. Before succeeding, you fail. It is normal. You should
make it your expectation. It is part of the process. Of course, it is painful,
especially when seeing the seemingly overwhelming success of everyone around
you. Personally, I had to stop going on Twitter because it was too painful to
see everyone going forward while I was stuck in the same place for so long. So I
feel like it is important to talk about this part of this story so that others
do not get disheartened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the rest of the article on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://csrc.kaist.ac.kr/blog/2020/10/21/painful-creativity&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CSRC
blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Checklist of &#39;How to Win Friends and Influence People&#39;</title>
      <link>/post/carnegie/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/carnegie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a summary of &amp;ldquo;How to Win Friends and Influence People&amp;rdquo; by Dale
Carnegie.
The goal of this book is obviously stated through its title
😜. Although at first sight, you might believe
this is achieved by tricking others, actually the basic answer is very
simple: just give your &lt;strong&gt;honest appreciation&lt;/strong&gt; to others. See the world with
their eyes, &lt;strong&gt;understand&lt;/strong&gt; them, and sincerely try to help them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principles taught in this book will work only when they come from the
heart. I am not advocating a bag of tricks. I am talking about a new way of
life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, even though this is simple in principle, it is quite far from our
first instinct. We tend to focus on ourselves, and me the first. So here I
want to make a kind checklist from the book 📃. This way anyone
can quickly go through it regularly and be sure to always have it fresh in
their mind. I would still recommend reading the book if you haven&amp;rsquo;t done it yet.
It will be easier to get in Carnegie&amp;rsquo;s mindset this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-fundamentals&#34;&gt;The Fundamentals&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this first part, Carnegie explains the base principles to apply. Then in
the following parts, the author gives more specific and directly applicable
advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-never-criticize&#34;&gt;1. Never Criticize&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While criticizing, you run into the risk of turning people against yourself,
for the improbable upside of getting them to do what you want. It rarely
works and is very likely to backfire on you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-praise-people&#34;&gt;2. &lt;em&gt;Praise&lt;/em&gt; People&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I consider my ability to arouse &lt;strong&gt;enthusiasm&lt;/strong&gt; among my people the
greatest asset I possess, and the way to develop the best that is in a person
is by &lt;strong&gt;appreciation&lt;/strong&gt; and encouragement. [&amp;hellip;] I believe in giving
&lt;strong&gt;incentives&lt;/strong&gt; to work.&amp;rdquo; Charles Schwab&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most people, a priority in life is to &lt;strong&gt;feel important&lt;/strong&gt;. By providing
them with this feeling, you give them a reason to do what you want. Just give
them your honest appreciation for their own personnality or their action and
they will feel their importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-arouse-an-eager-want&#34;&gt;3. Arouse an Eager Want&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one cares about what &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; want. People care about their interests. To be
able to &lt;strong&gt;influence&lt;/strong&gt; others, you need to &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; what matters to them.
And once you identify their needs, show them how to get it. First,
arouse an eager want, then show them how to obtain it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example when in an apparent contradiction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start positive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But &amp;hellip; describe the problem &lt;strong&gt;for them&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explain a solution &lt;strong&gt;for them&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;make-people-love-you&#34;&gt;Make People Love You&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s get into the more practical advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-show-genuine-interest&#34;&gt;1. Show Genuine Interest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dog makes its living by giving nothing to you but &lt;strong&gt;love&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, just show genuine love to others. It can be in little things, like
daily greetings. &lt;strong&gt;Do&lt;/strong&gt; things for others, give them time, energy and
thoughtfulness. Before you realize it, they will have given it back to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Careful&lt;/em&gt; though: always be sincere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-smile&#34;&gt;2. Smile&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It costs nothing but creates much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must have a good time meeting people if you expect them to have a good
time meeting you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-call-people-by-name&#34;&gt;3. Call People by &lt;em&gt;Name&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People place big importance on their own name. Remember it and call it
easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-be-an-active-listener&#34;&gt;4. Be an &lt;em&gt;Active Listener&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone wants an opportunity to expand their ego. So give them an
opportunity to do so by actively listening to them.
Be interested: Ask questions, encourage them to talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Letting people talk is a favor to them: it helps clarify their minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-find-and-talk-about-their-interest&#34;&gt;5. Find and Talk about Their &lt;em&gt;Interest&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking in terms of the other person&amp;rsquo;s interest pays off for both parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;6-make-others-feel-important&#34;&gt;6. Make Others &lt;em&gt;Feel Important&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every man I meet is my superior in some way. In that, I learn of him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Honestly&lt;/strong&gt; admire others. We all crave for importance.
Give to others what you would like to be given → To apply &lt;strong&gt;all the time&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;change-people-thinking&#34;&gt;Change People Thinking&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-you-cannot-win-an-argument&#34;&gt;1. You Cannot Win an Argument&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t win an argument. If you lose it, you lose it; If you win it, you
lose it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguing only creates &lt;strong&gt;resentment&lt;/strong&gt;. The other person may do what you want,
but they won&amp;rsquo;t do it with goodwill. They won&amp;rsquo;t change their way of thinking.
Just &lt;strong&gt;never tell them they are wrong&lt;/strong&gt;.
At least partially agree with them. Make them feel good. Promise to consider
their position. Show &lt;strong&gt;respect&lt;/strong&gt; for their opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are going to prove anything, don&amp;rsquo;t let anybody know it. Do it
subtly. [&amp;hellip;] With a few low-keyed suggestions at proper intervals, I let them
develop my system themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-willfully-admit-when-you-are-wrong&#34;&gt;2. Willfully &lt;em&gt;Admit&lt;/em&gt; when you are Wrong&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also quite likely that you are wrong. It happens surprisingly often.
And when we catch ourselves, let&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;admit it quickly and with enthusiasm&lt;/strong&gt;.
It will &lt;em&gt;surprise&lt;/em&gt; others and put them in a non-fighting mindset.
Astonishingly, we may get more from them this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-begin-friendly&#34;&gt;3. Begin &lt;em&gt;Friendly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the start of the conversation or presentation, start in a &amp;ldquo;friendly mode&amp;rdquo;.
It will put people in a positive mindset. They will be more inclined to see
the good side of what you say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-the-yes-yes-technique&#34;&gt;4. The &amp;ldquo;Yes, yes&amp;rdquo; Technique&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Famously used by Socrates: He often began conversation emphasizing the thing
which he knew the other person will agree with. Seeking others agreement with
a question, forces to &lt;em&gt;commit&lt;/em&gt; to your side. It creates a good atmosphere and
makes it easier for them to accept new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-let-others-talk&#34;&gt;5. Let Others Talk&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will make sure you &lt;strong&gt;understand&lt;/strong&gt; them. If you talk too much and do not
give the others enough opportunity to express themselves, you might get into
the wrong argument which may not matter to them. Just restrain yourself to an
&lt;em&gt;active listener&lt;/em&gt; position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even better, if you are subtle enough to guide them in their talk, you can
make &lt;em&gt;suggestions&lt;/em&gt; and give them the &lt;strong&gt;feeling of ownership of ideas&lt;/strong&gt; that
you provide them. Once they feel it is their idea, they will become their
strong supporter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;6-understand-others-point-of-view&#34;&gt;6. &lt;em&gt;Understand&lt;/em&gt; Others Point of View&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not condemn them. Any fool can do that. Try to understand them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is really the key to this book. Try to see things as others experience
them. This is the best way to find how to change their mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cooperativeness in conversation is achieved when you show that you consider
the other person&amp;rsquo;s ideas and feelings as &lt;strong&gt;important&lt;/strong&gt; as your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone craves for the sympathy of other people. Be &lt;strong&gt;sympathetic&lt;/strong&gt; to their
ideas. Welcome them with an open mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;7-appeal-to-nobler-motives&#34;&gt;7. Appeal to &lt;em&gt;Nobler Motives&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A person usually has two reasons for doing something: one that sounds
good, and a real one&amp;rdquo; J.P. Morgan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to change people, appeal to their &lt;strong&gt;nobler&lt;/strong&gt; motives. People are
honest and fair, or at least they want to feel so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;8-dramatize-use-showmanship&#34;&gt;8. &lt;em&gt;Dramatize&lt;/em&gt;, use Showmanship&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes your idea more &lt;strong&gt;vivid&lt;/strong&gt;. It makes abstractions more concrete and
thus easier to grasp. Numbers or concepts do not stick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;9-challenge-people&#34;&gt;9. &lt;em&gt;Challenge&lt;/em&gt; People&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carnegie advices using this when nothing else works. Stimulating competition,
challenging people will &lt;strong&gt;drive their desire to excel&lt;/strong&gt;. In the end, we are
all motivated to do the best we can in the task we achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;being-a-leader&#34;&gt;Being A Leader&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to change people without offending them or causing resentment?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-always-begin-with-praise&#34;&gt;1. Always Begin with &lt;em&gt;Praise&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only critic after you praise. You will set yourself as a friendly
figure and thus your point will be received with a more positive mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-praise-the-slight-improvement&#34;&gt;2. Praise the Slight Improvement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Praise as the power to &lt;strong&gt;inspire&lt;/strong&gt; people to go beyond what they thought they
could do. The more you use this power, the more they will feel encouraged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be &lt;em&gt;specific&lt;/em&gt; in your praise. It shows the other you are really sincere. Your
words are not empty, they have substance because you can precisely point what
is praiseworthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When criticism is minimized and praise emphasized, the good things people
do will be reinforced, and the poorer things will atrophy for lack of
attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-fake-it-till-they-make-it&#34;&gt;3. Fake It Till &lt;em&gt;They&lt;/em&gt; Make It&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you show you believe someone has a virtue, state it openly, they will want
to live up to the reputation you have given them! It will motivate them, give
them a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus, whenever they make mistakes, minimize it. Make it look like a small
thing, like something &lt;strong&gt;easy to overcome&lt;/strong&gt;. They may discover something they
thought was hard, it actually easy for them once you give them the strength
to &lt;strong&gt;go beyond their limits&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-criticize-indirectly&#34;&gt;4. Criticize Indirectly&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is harder to grasp. Basically, if you point mistakes directly,
people may resent you. Instead, only suggest it indirectly. Make the other
person understand your point by going around it. The danger is that you
wander off too far from your target and that they do not see the point you
critic at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example from the book I found quite helpful: A guy wrote a speech and asks
the opinion of his wife on it. The speech was quite bad because it would not
flow well as a spoken performance. Instead of directly saying so, his wife
said that it would make an excellent article. Praising it while making it
clear that it would be a boring speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-start-by-stating-your-mistakes&#34;&gt;5. Start by Stating &lt;em&gt;Your Mistakes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have seen several &lt;em&gt;starting tips&lt;/em&gt; so far. The way you start is
important, it sets the mood. It can open or close the mind of the other
person. So if you begin talking by criticizing yourself, you communicate to
the other that you are a fair and humble person. You are not a distant boss
too full of himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn&amp;rsquo;t nearly so difficult to listen to a recital of your faults if the
person criticizing begins by humbly admitting that he, &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt;, is far from
impeccable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;6-the-power-of-suggestions&#34;&gt;6. The Power of &lt;em&gt;Suggestions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one likes to receive orders. So instead, try to only suggest a way of
doing. Ask them questions that only hint at what you think would be a good
way of proceeding. People will be much happier doing things if they feel it
is &lt;em&gt;their decision&lt;/em&gt;. Or at least that they are involved in the decision
process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus, always try to &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; what &lt;em&gt;benefits them&lt;/em&gt;. Why would they be
happy of following your suggestions? How would it benefit them? Sincerely try
to match what would be a good outcome for them with what you want
to be accomplished. This way, others may be &lt;strong&gt;happy of doing what you
suggest&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;7-let-others-save-face&#34;&gt;7. Let Others &lt;em&gt;Save Face&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no right to say or do anything that diminishes a man in his own
eyes. What matters is not what I think of him, but what he thinks of himself.
Hurting a man dignity is a crime.&amp;quot; Antoine de Saint-Exupéry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you destroy other people&amp;rsquo;s ego, they will always resent you and never
follow you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these points are simple one by one. But all together they create a
system of communication which doesn&amp;rsquo;t come easily. It&amp;rsquo;s important to
&lt;strong&gt;practice&lt;/strong&gt; it as much as possible. In all our interactions. And there are
many recommendations, so it&amp;rsquo;s hard to keep them all in mind. So come back to
this list regularly to refresh your mind 😉.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antifragile: Why AI fails and alternative</title>
      <link>/post/antifragile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/antifragile/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;quick-summary&#34;&gt;Quick Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all want to &lt;strong&gt;predict&lt;/strong&gt; the future. Once we know what will happen, we can
prepare and take advantage of the situation and become stronger. For example,
if you know which stock will go up/down, you would make a lot of money. The
ability to predict is the foundation of science: experiment to find
&lt;em&gt;models&lt;/em&gt; that can forecast the future.
Nassim Taleb destroyed this idea in his book &amp;ldquo;The Black Swan&amp;rdquo;: The most
impactful events, the game changers, are unpredictable. Although we often use
post-rationalization to make it look like we could have foreseen the events
after the fact. For example, the 9/11 attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &amp;ldquo;Antifragile: Things That Gain from Disorder&amp;rdquo;, Taleb explains what we can
do when we cannot predict the future but know it will change everything big
time. The answer is in the title: we should build &lt;strong&gt;antifragile&lt;/strong&gt; system.
We know there will be shocks. Instead of predicting these shocks themselves
and lowering their consequences, we make systems that take advantage of them!
Systems that get stronger thanks to the shocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;personal-impact&#34;&gt;Personal Impact&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taleb directly speaks to me. While working doing research on

&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/publication/ankou/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ankou&lt;/a&gt; and

&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/publication/entropic/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Entropic&lt;/a&gt;, I often confronted
with this idea of how to deal with extremely rare events. In 2019, I got
passionate about &amp;ldquo;Complex System&amp;rdquo; theory: system with so many inner
interactions that their behavior cannot be well understood. I tried to read as
much as possible on the subject: Geoffrey West, John Holland, Stuart Kauffman,
and some others. I tried to understand &amp;ldquo;what can we do in this situation&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, we cannot use the usual scientific approach of decomposing systems
and then scaling up this understanding to predict the behavior of the whole
system. Complex systems can only be characterized with high level statistical
descriptors like &lt;em&gt;entropy&lt;/em&gt;. We are limited to description, we cannot predict.
And Taleb&amp;rsquo;s insight is a similar one: Complex systems, due to their many
interactions have hidden, unforeseeable and non-linear behaviors. Their
&lt;strong&gt;causal opacity&lt;/strong&gt; and non-linearity make them perfect &lt;strong&gt;Black Swan
generators&lt;/strong&gt;. And guess what, almost everything we deal with nowadays is
complex systems, are socio-economical system, most of the product we engineer
(that&amp;rsquo;s why we can&amp;rsquo;t seem to solve all bugs), and of course nature itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;solution&#34;&gt;Solution&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should stop trying to be smart. Stop trying to predict how systems are
going to react to this or that shock. We should go back to our real goal:
the &lt;strong&gt;payoff&lt;/strong&gt;. Focus back on what we get in the end. If we put ourselves in
an antifragile situation, we can benefit from future shocks, but we do not
need to plan for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-importance-of-options&#34;&gt;The Importance of Options&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Optionality is a substitute for intelligence.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The option is an agent of antifragility.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do we make ourselves antifragile? We give ourselves &lt;strong&gt;options&lt;/strong&gt;. We
often try to cut all which seems unnecessary, or redundant, to perform better
at some given metric. But maybe this metric won&amp;rsquo;t be so important tomorrow.
By having options, you give yourself more paths to explore in the future when
you&amp;rsquo;ll get more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taleb likes to use the &amp;ldquo;rational flâneur&amp;rdquo; metaphor: when you travel, instead
of having a two week plan of how you&amp;rsquo;ll visit this city or this country, you
just plan a few days forward. This way you have the freedom to plan the rest
of the trip when you acquire more information while you are already there.
You don&amp;rsquo;t know what kind of information you will acquire, you don&amp;rsquo;t know what
unexpected event can occur. By keeping a maximum of options available, you
make sure that whatever happens, you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to transform to your benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &amp;ldquo;option&amp;rdquo; solution can be reformulated in a &amp;lsquo;&lt;strong&gt;Trial and error&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rsquo; policy.
All the things you can try are your options. Notice that you still need some
rationality to try options that have some potential, and then recognize a
successful trial. Taleb is saying that we rely too much on models and
top-down logic, but not that science and formalization are never useful. We
still need some. Just much less of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in the end, this is exactly the &lt;em&gt;evolutionary heuristics&lt;/em&gt; we use for
fuzzers! Each seed is an option the fuzzer has. The fitness function is the
way we chose the potential &amp;ldquo;good options&amp;rdquo; for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;via-negativa&#34;&gt;Via Negativa&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Rule No. 1: Never lose money. Rule No. 2: Don’t forget rule No. 1&amp;rdquo;
Warren Buffet&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other way Taleb suggests to achieve antifragility is to &amp;ldquo;remove the bad
stuff&amp;rdquo;. It is not easy to predict what is going to happen, and it may be even
harder to take advantage of it. However, it is often quite simple to
&lt;strong&gt;detect fragility&lt;/strong&gt;. The via negativa way is: detect the bad and remove it.
This you are left with either robust, meaning that it does not have much
reaction to shocks, negatively or positively, or antifragile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;We know a lot more about what is wrong than what is right. Negative
knowledge is more robust to error than positive knowledge.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what he calls the &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;barbell&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; strategy. You have the robust part
which you can&amp;rsquo;t lose; it is your insurance. And you have the antifragile
part, which is riskier, but gives you exposure to different kinds of shocks
by being diversified, and makes your profit/payoff. This is not very
sophisticated, but in the end, &lt;strong&gt;less is more&lt;/strong&gt;. This technique was lightly
sketched out in &amp;ldquo;The Black Swan&amp;rdquo;, but without all of the fragility framework,
so it was hard to understand why it would work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not be a fool. Do not over-optimize your system thinking you got
everything under control. With a thin margin of safety, you risk losing it all.
You are never fully safe from a Black Swan unless you set your system up this
way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boosting Fuzzer Efficiency: An Information Theoretic Perspective</title>
      <link>/publication/entropic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/entropic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Entropic received the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://2020.esec-fse.org/program/program-esecfse-2020&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ACM SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper
Award&lt;/a&gt;! Furthermore,
its code was made the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/llvm/llvm-project/commit/f3c2e0bcee64b0905addaefe9cd0c9ad4d20ac6f&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;default schedule in
LibFuzzer&lt;/a&gt;
which powers 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/google/oss-fuzz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google&amp;rsquo;s OSSFuzz&lt;/a&gt; and

&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/microsoft/onefuzz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s OneFuzz&lt;/a&gt; 🚀.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we take the fundamental perspective of fuzzing as a learning
process. Suppose before fuzzing, we know nothing about the behaviors of a
program P: What does it do? Executing the first test input, we learn how P
behaves for this input. Executing the next input, we either observe the same
or discover a new behavior. As such, each execution reveals “some amount” of
information about P’s behaviors. A classic measure of information is
Shannon’s entropy. Measuring entropy allows us to quantify how much is
learned from each generated test input about the behaviors of the program.
Within a probabilistic model of fuzzing, we show how entropy also measures
fuzzer efficiency. Specifically, it measures the general rate at which the
fuzzer discovers new behaviors. Intuitively, efficient fuzzers maximize
information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this information theoretic perspective, we develop En- tropic, an
entropy-based power schedule for greybox fuzzing which assigns more energy to
seeds that maximize information. We implemented Entropic into the popular
greybox fuzzer LibFuzzer. Our experiments with more than 250 open-source
programs (60 million LoC) demonstrate a substantially improved efficiency and
confirm our hypothesis that an efficient fuzzer maximizes informa- tion.
Entropic has been independently evaluated and invited for integration into
main-line LibFuzzer. Entropic will run on more than 25,000 machines fuzzing
hundreds of security-critical software systems simultaneously and
continuously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
body{ /* Normal  */
    font-size: 13pt;
}
&lt;/style&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ankou: Guiding Grey-box Fuzzing towards Combinatorial Difference</title>
      <link>/publication/ankou/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ankou/</guid>
      <description>&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
body{ /* Normal  */
    font-size: 13pt;
}
&lt;/style&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Art, Science, and Engineering of Fuzzing: A Survey</title>
      <link>/publication/survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/survey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Among the many software testing techniques available today, &lt;em&gt;fuzzing&lt;/em&gt; has
remained highly popular due to its conceptual simplicity, its low barrier to
deployment, and its vast amount of empirical evidence in discovering real-world
software vulnerabilities.
At a high level, fuzzing refers to a process of repeatedly running a program
with generated inputs that may be syntactically or semantically malformed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8863940&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Our survey&lt;/a&gt; shows the fuzzing
community is extremely vibrant.
The recent surge of work by researchers and practitioners alike has made it
difficult to gain a comprehensive and coherent view of fuzzing. Thus, it is easy
to lose track of the design decisions and potentially important tweaks performed
in each tool and paper.
Furthermore, there has been an observable fragmentation in the terminology used
by various fuzzers. For example, test case &amp;ldquo;minimization&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;reduction&amp;rdquo;
are often used interchangeably. Such fragmentation makes it difficult to
discover and disseminate knowledge and may severely hinder the progress in
fuzzing research in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help preserve and bring coherence to the vast literature of fuzzing, this
paper presented a unified, general-purpose model of fuzzing together with a
taxonomy of the current literature.
Our terminology is chosen to closely reflect the current predominant usages, and
our model is designed to suit a large number of fuzzing tasks.
We surveyed academic papers from the major Security and Software Engineering
conferences in the last 10 years, as well as projects having more than 100 stars
on GitHub.
The paper methodically explores the design decisions at every stage of the model
by surveying the related literature and innovations that make modern-day fuzzers
effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;companion-website&#34;&gt;Companion Website&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our contribution in this work is more than just the survey. Upon receiving the
acceptance notice, we have started building 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://fuzzing-survey.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a companion
website&lt;/a&gt;. It is backed by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SoftSec-KAIST/Fuzzing-Survey&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a repository at
GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, which contains the
genealogy and the classification data of the surveyed fuzzers in the JSON
format. We plan to keep this site up-to-date periodically through investing our
own effort and accepting contributions from the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
body{ /* Normal  */
    font-size: 13pt;
}
&lt;/style&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compiling Linux Kernel with Clang</title>
      <link>/post/kernel_clang_compile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/kernel_clang_compile/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone. This is my first &amp;lsquo;technical&amp;rsquo; blog post. I saw some people saying it
helps growing your explanation skills which I sincerely lack. Thus, I decided
next I struggle doing something because I feel it&amp;rsquo;s quite undocumented, I&amp;rsquo;ll try
to make a post and explain how I did it. If even one person reads this and it&amp;rsquo;s
even remotely useful to them, I&amp;rsquo;ll consider the job done. Ask any question, I&amp;rsquo;ll
be happy to answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now down to the topic. I have trying to compile the kernel with clang ever since
I have seen the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://lwn.net/Articles/734071/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LWN.net article&lt;/a&gt; on the
topic. It says that you &amp;lsquo;just&amp;rsquo; need to go and compile your kernel with &lt;code&gt;make CC=clang&lt;/code&gt;. So I went into the linux sources I had at this time (something around
4.9.60) and type the command. Obviously it didn&amp;rsquo;t work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, it&amp;rsquo;s not that much complicated. There are two requirements to
compiling your kernel with clang:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the right source and configuration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the right version of clang.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything is very well summarized on a LKML post from last November:

&lt;a href=&#34;https://lkml.org/lkml/2017/11/22/943&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://lkml.org/lkml/2017/11/22/943&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concerning the source, I went for the simplest path: getting the latest stable
version of the kernel with default configuration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;git clone git://git.kernel.org/pub/scm/linux/kernel/git/stable/linux-stable.git
cd linux-stable
git checkout v4.14.15
make defconfig
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I&amp;rsquo;m on x86. If you want to compile for ARM64, it seems a bit more
complicated. I didn&amp;rsquo;t try it but you might want to look for the android source
that have not been upstreamed yet. Posting here because it&amp;rsquo;s not linked in the
Matthias Kaehlcke&amp;rsquo;s LKML post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://android.googlesource.com/kernel/common.git/&amp;#43;log/android-4.9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://android.googlesource.com/kernel/common.git/+log/android-4.9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://android.googlesource.com/kernel/common.git/&amp;#43;log/android-4.4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://android.googlesource.com/kernel/common.git/+log/android-4.4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There also other documentation made by Google 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://apt.llvm.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
which shows how to compile the kernel with KASAN and KCOV. Didn&amp;rsquo;t dig into that
but could be useful to someone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for other configuration than just the default one, I didn&amp;rsquo;t
try that and I think it&amp;rsquo;s really and a case by case basis. You are going to have
to dig a little bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for the version of clang, you need clang 5 or more. I on Debian Stretch for
which LLVM has precompiled binary (see here if you are on another OS version).
So add them to your source list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;sudo vim /etc/apt/sources.list 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then add:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;deb http://apt.llvm.org/stretch/ llvm-toolchain-stretch-6.0 main
deb-src http://apt.llvm.org/stretch/ llvm-toolchain-stretch-6.0 main
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you can install clang:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get install clang-6.0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not on Debian/Ubuntu, I am not sure whether or not there is another
solution than just compiling LLVM directly (see 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://clang.llvm.org/get_started.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we have the source and the compiler, so we are ready to compile. Go in
your linux-stable/ folder and:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;make CC=clang-6.0 -j4 bzImage
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just wanted the &lt;code&gt;bzImage&lt;/code&gt; to boot, but you remove it if you want to compile
everything.
&lt;code&gt;-j4&lt;/code&gt; because gain time by making compilation parallel&amp;hellip; Now I don&amp;rsquo;t know how you
plan to use your clang compiled kernel, but just to check it&amp;rsquo;s usable, I run it
with qemu:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;qemu-system-x86_64 -kernel arch/x86/boot/bzImage -nographic -serial mon:stdio -append &#39;console=ttyS0&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And since we didn&amp;rsquo;t provide the -initrd option, it will crash at the end with
something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---[ end Kernel panic - not syncing: VFS: Unable to mount root fs on unknown-block(0,0)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of guides on how to use your kernel, not the goal here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That will conclude my first post. Hopefully it was clear enough. Don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate
to contact me by any mean if you have any question or problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Domain Isolated Kernel: A lightweight sandbox for untrusted kernel extensions</title>
      <link>/publication/dikernel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/dikernel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
body{ /* Normal  */
    font-size: 13pt;
}
&lt;/style&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
