<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>1 | Valentin Manès</title>
    <link>/publication_types/1/</link>
      <atom:link href="/publication_types/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>1</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/profile.jpg</url>
      <title>1</title>
      <link>/publication_types/1/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boosting Fuzzer Efficiency: An Information Theoretic Perspective</title>
      <link>/publication/entropic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/entropic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Entropic received the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://2020.esec-fse.org/program/program-esecfse-2020&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ACM SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper
Award&lt;/a&gt;! Furthermore,
its code was made the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/llvm/llvm-project/commit/f3c2e0bcee64b0905addaefe9cd0c9ad4d20ac6f&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;default schedule in
LibFuzzer&lt;/a&gt;
which powers 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/google/oss-fuzz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google&amp;rsquo;s OSSFuzz&lt;/a&gt; and

&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/microsoft/onefuzz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s OneFuzz&lt;/a&gt; 🚀.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we take the fundamental perspective of fuzzing as a learning
process. Suppose before fuzzing, we know nothing about the behaviors of a
program P: What does it do? Executing the first test input, we learn how P
behaves for this input. Executing the next input, we either observe the same
or discover a new behavior. As such, each execution reveals “some amount” of
information about P’s behaviors. A classic measure of information is
Shannon’s entropy. Measuring entropy allows us to quantify how much is
learned from each generated test input about the behaviors of the program.
Within a probabilistic model of fuzzing, we show how entropy also measures
fuzzer efficiency. Specifically, it measures the general rate at which the
fuzzer discovers new behaviors. Intuitively, efficient fuzzers maximize
information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this information theoretic perspective, we develop En- tropic, an
entropy-based power schedule for greybox fuzzing which assigns more energy to
seeds that maximize information. We implemented Entropic into the popular
greybox fuzzer LibFuzzer. Our experiments with more than 250 open-source
programs (60 million LoC) demonstrate a substantially improved efficiency and
confirm our hypothesis that an efficient fuzzer maximizes informa- tion.
Entropic has been independently evaluated and invited for integration into
main-line LibFuzzer. Entropic will run on more than 25,000 machines fuzzing
hundreds of security-critical software systems simultaneously and
continuously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
body{ /* Normal  */
    font-size: 13pt;
}
&lt;/style&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ankou: Guiding Grey-box Fuzzing towards Combinatorial Difference</title>
      <link>/publication/ankou/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ankou/</guid>
      <description>&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
body{ /* Normal  */
    font-size: 13pt;
}
&lt;/style&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
