<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Valentin Manès</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/profile_valentin.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trop débordé pour un mouton ? Alors ce n&#39;est pas pour vous</title>
      <link>/post/petit_prince/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/petit_prince/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ça fait 18 mois que je travaille sur ce projet. J&amp;rsquo;ai misé toute ma carrière dessus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Je suis dans la dernière ligne droite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma femme me dérange avec des histoires de réservation d’hôtel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🧨 J&amp;rsquo;explose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elle ne voit pas que ce projet est primordial ? Que je n&amp;rsquo;ai pas le temps pour ce genre de détail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;400px&#34; src=&#34;/img/petit_prince/rose.jpeg&#34;
alt=&#34;une rose qui pique&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Les épines, à quoi servent-elles ?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le petit prince ne renonce jamais à une question. J’étais irrité par mon boulon et je répondis n&amp;rsquo;importe quoi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;400px&#34; src=&#34;/img/petit_prince/petit_prince_book.jpeg&#34;
alt=&#34;Le Petit Prince (couverture)&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C&amp;rsquo;est ce comportement que dénonce Saint-Exupéry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le cerveau humain est une machine à créer (et résoudre) des problèmes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On croit qu&amp;rsquo;une fois que l&amp;rsquo;on aura LE problème en face de nous, notre vie sera le paradis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Si seulement j&amp;rsquo;avais la solution&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mauvaise nouvelle : Le monde ne peut pas être parfait. Il y aura toujours une imperfection à corriger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Tout le malheur des hommes vient de ne savoir pas demeurer en repos, dans une chambre.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; — Blaise Pascal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Si je regarde mon problème de plus près, il ne fait plus beaucoup de sens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;À quoi cela te sert-il de posséder les étoiles ?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ça me sert à être riche.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Et à quoi cela te sert-il d’être riche ?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;À acheter d&amp;rsquo;autres étoiles.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Celui-là, se dit en lui-même le petit prince, il raisonne un peu comme mon ivrogne.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-le-bonheur-juste-là&#34;&gt;🙋 Le Bonheur, Juste Là&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le Petit Prince, ce n&amp;rsquo;est pas juste un livre critique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La solution nous vient de monsieur le renard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;600px&#34; src=&#34;/img/petit_prince/renard.jpeg&#34;
alt=&#34;La sagesse du Renard&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Les hommes n&amp;rsquo;ont plus le temps de rien connaître. Ils achètent des choses toutes faites chez les marchands. Mais comme il n&amp;rsquo;existe point de marchands d&amp;rsquo;amis, les hommes n&amp;rsquo;ont plus d&amp;rsquo;amis. Si tu veux un ami, apprivoise-moi !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La générosité, la gratitude, l&amp;rsquo;amour. Prendre le temps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La pénurie de 2021, ce n&amp;rsquo;est pas le gazole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encore plus aujourd&amp;rsquo;hui qu’à l’époque de Saint-Exupéry, ce qui nous manque c&amp;rsquo;est plus d’appréciation pour ce que nous avons déjà.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peu importe les problèmes de notre quotidien. Si nous avons quelqu&amp;rsquo;un à chérir, nous avons tout ce qu&amp;rsquo;il nous faut pour être heureux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On ne voit bien qu&amp;rsquo;avec le cœur. L&amp;rsquo;essentiel est invisible pour les yeux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le savoir c&amp;rsquo;est une chose. Mais quand je vois comment j&amp;rsquo;ai réagi avec ma femme, clairement ce n&amp;rsquo;est pas assez.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L&amp;rsquo;amour se pratique.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quotidiennement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bien à propos, ma cousine m&amp;rsquo;a envoyé un &amp;ldquo;calendrier de l&amp;rsquo;avent de bienveillance&amp;rdquo;. Parfait pour une première mise en pratique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&#34;600px&#34; src=&#34;/img/petit_prince/avent.jpeg&#34;
alt=&#34;Pratiquer l&#39;Amour Tous les Jours&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Valentin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PS&lt;/strong&gt; : L&amp;rsquo;amour se partage. Alors envoyez cet article à vos amis 🤲&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Si vous voulez recevoir plus de mail comme celui-ci, vous pouvez vous inscrire sur 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mimima.fr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;mimima.fr&lt;/a&gt; (si vous n’êtes pas déjà inscrit)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ankou: Painful Creativity</title>
      <link>/post/ankou_creativity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/ankou_creativity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you want to increase your success rate, double your failure rate.”
&lt;em&gt;Thomas J. Watson, IBM CEO&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not said enough. Before succeeding, you fail. It is normal. You should
make it your expectation. It is part of the process. Of course, it is painful,
especially when seeing the seemingly overwhelming success of everyone around
you. Personally, I had to stop going on Twitter because it was too painful to
see everyone going forward while I was stuck in the same place for so long. So I
feel like it is important to talk about this part of this story so that others
do not get disheartened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the rest of the article on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://csrc.kaist.ac.kr/blog/2020/10/21/painful-creativity&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CSRC
blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Checklist of &#39;How to Win Friends and Influence People&#39;</title>
      <link>/post/carnegie/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/carnegie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a summary of &amp;ldquo;How to Win Friends and Influence People&amp;rdquo; by Dale
Carnegie.
The goal of this book is obviously stated through its title
😜. Although at first sight, you might believe
this is achieved by tricking others, actually the basic answer is very
simple: just give your &lt;strong&gt;honest appreciation&lt;/strong&gt; to others. See the world with
their eyes, &lt;strong&gt;understand&lt;/strong&gt; them, and sincerely try to help them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principles taught in this book will work only when they come from the
heart. I am not advocating a bag of tricks. I am talking about a new way of
life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, even though this is simple in principle, it is quite far from our
first instinct. We tend to focus on ourselves, and me the first. So here I
want to make a kind checklist from the book 📃. This way anyone
can quickly go through it regularly and be sure to always have it fresh in
their mind. I would still recommend reading the book if you haven&amp;rsquo;t done it yet.
It will be easier to get in Carnegie&amp;rsquo;s mindset this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-fundamentals&#34;&gt;The Fundamentals&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this first part, Carnegie explains the base principles to apply. Then in
the following parts, the author gives more specific and directly applicable
advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-never-criticize&#34;&gt;1. Never Criticize&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While criticizing, you run into the risk of turning people against yourself,
for the improbable upside of getting them to do what you want. It rarely
works and is very likely to backfire on you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-praise-people&#34;&gt;2. &lt;em&gt;Praise&lt;/em&gt; People&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I consider my ability to arouse &lt;strong&gt;enthusiasm&lt;/strong&gt; among my people the
greatest asset I possess, and the way to develop the best that is in a person
is by &lt;strong&gt;appreciation&lt;/strong&gt; and encouragement. [&amp;hellip;] I believe in giving
&lt;strong&gt;incentives&lt;/strong&gt; to work.&amp;rdquo; Charles Schwab&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most people, a priority in life is to &lt;strong&gt;feel important&lt;/strong&gt;. By providing
them with this feeling, you give them a reason to do what you want. Just give
them your honest appreciation for their own personnality or their action and
they will feel their importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-arouse-an-eager-want&#34;&gt;3. Arouse an Eager Want&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one cares about what &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; want. People care about their interests. To be
able to &lt;strong&gt;influence&lt;/strong&gt; others, you need to &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; what matters to them.
And once you identify their needs, show them how to get it. First,
arouse an eager want, then show them how to obtain it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example when in an apparent contradiction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start positive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But &amp;hellip; describe the problem &lt;strong&gt;for them&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explain a solution &lt;strong&gt;for them&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;make-people-love-you&#34;&gt;Make People Love You&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s get into the more practical advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-show-genuine-interest&#34;&gt;1. Show Genuine Interest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dog makes its living by giving nothing to you but &lt;strong&gt;love&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, just show genuine love to others. It can be in little things, like
daily greetings. &lt;strong&gt;Do&lt;/strong&gt; things for others, give them time, energy and
thoughtfulness. Before you realize it, they will have given it back to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Careful&lt;/em&gt; though: always be sincere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-smile&#34;&gt;2. Smile&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It costs nothing but creates much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must have a good time meeting people if you expect them to have a good
time meeting you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-call-people-by-name&#34;&gt;3. Call People by &lt;em&gt;Name&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People place big importance on their own name. Remember it and call it
easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-be-an-active-listener&#34;&gt;4. Be an &lt;em&gt;Active Listener&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone wants an opportunity to expand their ego. So give them an
opportunity to do so by actively listening to them.
Be interested: Ask questions, encourage them to talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Letting people talk is a favor to them: it helps clarify their minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-find-and-talk-about-their-interest&#34;&gt;5. Find and Talk about Their &lt;em&gt;Interest&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking in terms of the other person&amp;rsquo;s interest pays off for both parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;6-make-others-feel-important&#34;&gt;6. Make Others &lt;em&gt;Feel Important&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every man I meet is my superior in some way. In that, I learn of him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Honestly&lt;/strong&gt; admire others. We all crave for importance.
Give to others what you would like to be given → To apply &lt;strong&gt;all the time&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;change-people-thinking&#34;&gt;Change People Thinking&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-you-cannot-win-an-argument&#34;&gt;1. You Cannot Win an Argument&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t win an argument. If you lose it, you lose it; If you win it, you
lose it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguing only creates &lt;strong&gt;resentment&lt;/strong&gt;. The other person may do what you want,
but they won&amp;rsquo;t do it with goodwill. They won&amp;rsquo;t change their way of thinking.
Just &lt;strong&gt;never tell them they are wrong&lt;/strong&gt;.
At least partially agree with them. Make them feel good. Promise to consider
their position. Show &lt;strong&gt;respect&lt;/strong&gt; for their opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are going to prove anything, don&amp;rsquo;t let anybody know it. Do it
subtly. [&amp;hellip;] With a few low-keyed suggestions at proper intervals, I let them
develop my system themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-willfully-admit-when-you-are-wrong&#34;&gt;2. Willfully &lt;em&gt;Admit&lt;/em&gt; when you are Wrong&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also quite likely that you are wrong. It happens surprisingly often.
And when we catch ourselves, let&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;admit it quickly and with enthusiasm&lt;/strong&gt;.
It will &lt;em&gt;surprise&lt;/em&gt; others and put them in a non-fighting mindset.
Astonishingly, we may get more from them this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-begin-friendly&#34;&gt;3. Begin &lt;em&gt;Friendly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the start of the conversation or presentation, start in a &amp;ldquo;friendly mode&amp;rdquo;.
It will put people in a positive mindset. They will be more inclined to see
the good side of what you say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-the-yes-yes-technique&#34;&gt;4. The &amp;ldquo;Yes, yes&amp;rdquo; Technique&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Famously used by Socrates: He often began conversation emphasizing the thing
which he knew the other person will agree with. Seeking others agreement with
a question, forces to &lt;em&gt;commit&lt;/em&gt; to your side. It creates a good atmosphere and
makes it easier for them to accept new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-let-others-talk&#34;&gt;5. Let Others Talk&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will make sure you &lt;strong&gt;understand&lt;/strong&gt; them. If you talk too much and do not
give the others enough opportunity to express themselves, you might get into
the wrong argument which may not matter to them. Just restrain yourself to an
&lt;em&gt;active listener&lt;/em&gt; position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even better, if you are subtle enough to guide them in their talk, you can
make &lt;em&gt;suggestions&lt;/em&gt; and give them the &lt;strong&gt;feeling of ownership of ideas&lt;/strong&gt; that
you provide them. Once they feel it is their idea, they will become their
strong supporter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;6-understand-others-point-of-view&#34;&gt;6. &lt;em&gt;Understand&lt;/em&gt; Others Point of View&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not condemn them. Any fool can do that. Try to understand them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is really the key to this book. Try to see things as others experience
them. This is the best way to find how to change their mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cooperativeness in conversation is achieved when you show that you consider
the other person&amp;rsquo;s ideas and feelings as &lt;strong&gt;important&lt;/strong&gt; as your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone craves for the sympathy of other people. Be &lt;strong&gt;sympathetic&lt;/strong&gt; to their
ideas. Welcome them with an open mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;7-appeal-to-nobler-motives&#34;&gt;7. Appeal to &lt;em&gt;Nobler Motives&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A person usually has two reasons for doing something: one that sounds
good, and a real one&amp;rdquo; J.P. Morgan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to change people, appeal to their &lt;strong&gt;nobler&lt;/strong&gt; motives. People are
honest and fair, or at least they want to feel so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;8-dramatize-use-showmanship&#34;&gt;8. &lt;em&gt;Dramatize&lt;/em&gt;, use Showmanship&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes your idea more &lt;strong&gt;vivid&lt;/strong&gt;. It makes abstractions more concrete and
thus easier to grasp. Numbers or concepts do not stick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;9-challenge-people&#34;&gt;9. &lt;em&gt;Challenge&lt;/em&gt; People&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carnegie advices using this when nothing else works. Stimulating competition,
challenging people will &lt;strong&gt;drive their desire to excel&lt;/strong&gt;. In the end, we are
all motivated to do the best we can in the task we achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;being-a-leader&#34;&gt;Being A Leader&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to change people without offending them or causing resentment?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-always-begin-with-praise&#34;&gt;1. Always Begin with &lt;em&gt;Praise&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only critic after you praise. You will set yourself as a friendly
figure and thus your point will be received with a more positive mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-praise-the-slight-improvement&#34;&gt;2. Praise the Slight Improvement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Praise as the power to &lt;strong&gt;inspire&lt;/strong&gt; people to go beyond what they thought they
could do. The more you use this power, the more they will feel encouraged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be &lt;em&gt;specific&lt;/em&gt; in your praise. It shows the other you are really sincere. Your
words are not empty, they have substance because you can precisely point what
is praiseworthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When criticism is minimized and praise emphasized, the good things people
do will be reinforced, and the poorer things will atrophy for lack of
attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-fake-it-till-they-make-it&#34;&gt;3. Fake It Till &lt;em&gt;They&lt;/em&gt; Make It&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you show you believe someone has a virtue, state it openly, they will want
to live up to the reputation you have given them! It will motivate them, give
them a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus, whenever they make mistakes, minimize it. Make it look like a small
thing, like something &lt;strong&gt;easy to overcome&lt;/strong&gt;. They may discover something they
thought was hard, it actually easy for them once you give them the strength
to &lt;strong&gt;go beyond their limits&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-criticize-indirectly&#34;&gt;4. Criticize Indirectly&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is harder to grasp. Basically, if you point mistakes directly,
people may resent you. Instead, only suggest it indirectly. Make the other
person understand your point by going around it. The danger is that you
wander off too far from your target and that they do not see the point you
critic at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example from the book I found quite helpful: A guy wrote a speech and asks
the opinion of his wife on it. The speech was quite bad because it would not
flow well as a spoken performance. Instead of directly saying so, his wife
said that it would make an excellent article. Praising it while making it
clear that it would be a boring speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-start-by-stating-your-mistakes&#34;&gt;5. Start by Stating &lt;em&gt;Your Mistakes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have seen several &lt;em&gt;starting tips&lt;/em&gt; so far. The way you start is
important, it sets the mood. It can open or close the mind of the other
person. So if you begin talking by criticizing yourself, you communicate to
the other that you are a fair and humble person. You are not a distant boss
too full of himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn&amp;rsquo;t nearly so difficult to listen to a recital of your faults if the
person criticizing begins by humbly admitting that he, &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt;, is far from
impeccable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;6-the-power-of-suggestions&#34;&gt;6. The Power of &lt;em&gt;Suggestions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one likes to receive orders. So instead, try to only suggest a way of
doing. Ask them questions that only hint at what you think would be a good
way of proceeding. People will be much happier doing things if they feel it
is &lt;em&gt;their decision&lt;/em&gt;. Or at least that they are involved in the decision
process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus, always try to &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; what &lt;em&gt;benefits them&lt;/em&gt;. Why would they be
happy of following your suggestions? How would it benefit them? Sincerely try
to match what would be a good outcome for them with what you want
to be accomplished. This way, others may be &lt;strong&gt;happy of doing what you
suggest&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;7-let-others-save-face&#34;&gt;7. Let Others &lt;em&gt;Save Face&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no right to say or do anything that diminishes a man in his own
eyes. What matters is not what I think of him, but what he thinks of himself.
Hurting a man dignity is a crime.&amp;rdquo; Antoine de Saint-Exupéry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you destroy other people&amp;rsquo;s ego, they will always resent you and never
follow you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these points are simple one by one. But all together they create a
system of communication which doesn&amp;rsquo;t come easily. It&amp;rsquo;s important to
&lt;strong&gt;practice&lt;/strong&gt; it as much as possible. In all our interactions. And there are
many recommendations, so it&amp;rsquo;s hard to keep them all in mind. So come back to
this list regularly to refresh your mind 😉.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antifragile: Why AI fails and alternative</title>
      <link>/post/antifragile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/antifragile/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;quick-summary&#34;&gt;Quick Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all want to &lt;strong&gt;predict&lt;/strong&gt; the future. Once we know what will happen, we can
prepare and take advantage of the situation and become stronger. For example,
if you know which stock will go up/down, you would make a lot of money. The
ability to predict is the foundation of science: experiment to find
&lt;em&gt;models&lt;/em&gt; that can forecast the future.
Nassim Taleb destroyed this idea in his book &amp;ldquo;The Black Swan&amp;rdquo;: The most
impactful events, the game changers, are unpredictable. Although we often use
post-rationalization to make it look like we could have foreseen the events
after the fact. For example, the 9/11 attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &amp;ldquo;Antifragile: Things That Gain from Disorder&amp;rdquo;, Taleb explains what we can
do when we cannot predict the future but know it will change everything big
time. The answer is in the title: we should build &lt;strong&gt;antifragile&lt;/strong&gt; system.
We know there will be shocks. Instead of predicting these shocks themselves
and lowering their consequences, we make systems that take advantage of them!
Systems that get stronger thanks to the shocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;personal-impact&#34;&gt;Personal Impact&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taleb directly speaks to me. While working doing research on

&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/publication/ankou/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ankou&lt;/a&gt; and

&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/publication/entropic/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Entropic&lt;/a&gt;, I often confronted
with this idea of how to deal with extremely rare events. In 2019, I got
passionate about &amp;ldquo;Complex System&amp;rdquo; theory: system with so many inner
interactions that their behavior cannot be well understood. I tried to read as
much as possible on the subject: Geoffrey West, John Holland, Stuart Kauffman,
and some others. I tried to understand &amp;ldquo;what can we do in this situation&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, we cannot use the usual scientific approach of decomposing systems
and then scaling up this understanding to predict the behavior of the whole
system. Complex systems can only be characterized with high level statistical
descriptors like &lt;em&gt;entropy&lt;/em&gt;. We are limited to description, we cannot predict.
And Taleb&amp;rsquo;s insight is a similar one: Complex systems, due to their many
interactions have hidden, unforeseeable and non-linear behaviors. Their
&lt;strong&gt;causal opacity&lt;/strong&gt; and non-linearity make them perfect &lt;strong&gt;Black Swan
generators&lt;/strong&gt;. And guess what, almost everything we deal with nowadays is
complex systems, are socio-economical system, most of the product we engineer
(that&amp;rsquo;s why we can&amp;rsquo;t seem to solve all bugs), and of course nature itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;solution&#34;&gt;Solution&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should stop trying to be smart. Stop trying to predict how systems are
going to react to this or that shock. We should go back to our real goal:
the &lt;strong&gt;payoff&lt;/strong&gt;. Focus back on what we get in the end. If we put ourselves in
an antifragile situation, we can benefit from future shocks, but we do not
need to plan for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-importance-of-options&#34;&gt;The Importance of Options&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Optionality is a substitute for intelligence.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The option is an agent of antifragility.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do we make ourselves antifragile? We give ourselves &lt;strong&gt;options&lt;/strong&gt;. We
often try to cut all which seems unnecessary, or redundant, to perform better
at some given metric. But maybe this metric won&amp;rsquo;t be so important tomorrow.
By having options, you give yourself more paths to explore in the future when
you&amp;rsquo;ll get more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taleb likes to use the &amp;ldquo;rational flâneur&amp;rdquo; metaphor: when you travel, instead
of having a two week plan of how you&amp;rsquo;ll visit this city or this country, you
just plan a few days forward. This way you have the freedom to plan the rest
of the trip when you acquire more information while you are already there.
You don&amp;rsquo;t know what kind of information you will acquire, you don&amp;rsquo;t know what
unexpected event can occur. By keeping a maximum of options available, you
make sure that whatever happens, you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to transform to your benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &amp;ldquo;option&amp;rdquo; solution can be reformulated in a &amp;lsquo;&lt;strong&gt;Trial and error&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rsquo; policy.
All the things you can try are your options. Notice that you still need some
rationality to try options that have some potential, and then recognize a
successful trial. Taleb is saying that we rely too much on models and
top-down logic, but not that science and formalization are never useful. We
still need some. Just much less of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in the end, this is exactly the &lt;em&gt;evolutionary heuristics&lt;/em&gt; we use for
fuzzers! Each seed is an option the fuzzer has. The fitness function is the
way we chose the potential &amp;ldquo;good options&amp;rdquo; for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;via-negativa&#34;&gt;Via Negativa&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Rule No. 1: Never lose money. Rule No. 2: Don’t forget rule No. 1&amp;rdquo;
Warren Buffet&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other way Taleb suggests to achieve antifragility is to &amp;ldquo;remove the bad
stuff&amp;rdquo;. It is not easy to predict what is going to happen, and it may be even
harder to take advantage of it. However, it is often quite simple to
&lt;strong&gt;detect fragility&lt;/strong&gt;. The via negativa way is: detect the bad and remove it.
This you are left with either robust, meaning that it does not have much
reaction to shocks, negatively or positively, or antifragile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;We know a lot more about what is wrong than what is right. Negative
knowledge is more robust to error than positive knowledge.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what he calls the &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;barbell&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; strategy. You have the robust part
which you can&amp;rsquo;t lose; it is your insurance. And you have the antifragile
part, which is riskier, but gives you exposure to different kinds of shocks
by being diversified, and makes your profit/payoff. This is not very
sophisticated, but in the end, &lt;strong&gt;less is more&lt;/strong&gt;. This technique was lightly
sketched out in &amp;ldquo;The Black Swan&amp;rdquo;, but without all of the fragility framework,
so it was hard to understand why it would work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not be a fool. Do not over-optimize your system thinking you got
everything under control. With a thin margin of safety, you risk losing it all.
You are never fully safe from a Black Swan unless you set your system up this
way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compiling Linux Kernel with Clang</title>
      <link>/post/kernel_clang_compile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/kernel_clang_compile/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone. This is my first &amp;lsquo;technical&amp;rsquo; blog post. I saw some people saying it
helps growing your explanation skills which I sincerely lack. Thus, I decided
next I struggle doing something because I feel it&amp;rsquo;s quite undocumented, I&amp;rsquo;ll try
to make a post and explain how I did it. If even one person reads this and it&amp;rsquo;s
even remotely useful to them, I&amp;rsquo;ll consider the job done. Ask any question, I&amp;rsquo;ll
be happy to answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now down to the topic. I have trying to compile the kernel with clang ever since
I have seen the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://lwn.net/Articles/734071/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LWN.net article&lt;/a&gt; on the
topic. It says that you &amp;lsquo;just&amp;rsquo; need to go and compile your kernel with &lt;code&gt;make CC=clang&lt;/code&gt;. So I went into the linux sources I had at this time (something around
4.9.60) and type the command. Obviously it didn&amp;rsquo;t work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, it&amp;rsquo;s not that much complicated. There are two requirements to
compiling your kernel with clang:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the right source and configuration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the right version of clang.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything is very well summarized on a LKML post from last November:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://lkml.org/lkml/2017/11/22/943&#34;&gt;https://lkml.org/lkml/2017/11/22/943&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concerning the source, I went for the simplest path: getting the latest stable
version of the kernel with default configuration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;git clone git://git.kernel.org/pub/scm/linux/kernel/git/stable/linux-stable.git
cd linux-stable
git checkout v4.14.15
make defconfig
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I&amp;rsquo;m on x86. If you want to compile for ARM64, it seems a bit more
complicated. I didn&amp;rsquo;t try it but you might want to look for the android source
that have not been upstreamed yet. Posting here because it&amp;rsquo;s not linked in the
Matthias Kaehlcke&amp;rsquo;s LKML post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://android.googlesource.com/kernel/common.git/+log/android-4.9&#34;&gt;https://android.googlesource.com/kernel/common.git/+log/android-4.9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://android.googlesource.com/kernel/common.git/+log/android-4.4&#34;&gt;https://android.googlesource.com/kernel/common.git/+log/android-4.4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There also other documentation made by Google 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://apt.llvm.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
which shows how to compile the kernel with KASAN and KCOV. Didn&amp;rsquo;t dig into that
but could be useful to someone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for other configuration than just the default one, I didn&amp;rsquo;t
try that and I think it&amp;rsquo;s really and a case by case basis. You are going to have
to dig a little bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for the version of clang, you need clang 5 or more. I on Debian Stretch for
which LLVM has precompiled binary (see here if you are on another OS version).
So add them to your source list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;sudo vim /etc/apt/sources.list 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then add:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;deb http://apt.llvm.org/stretch/ llvm-toolchain-stretch-6.0 main
deb-src http://apt.llvm.org/stretch/ llvm-toolchain-stretch-6.0 main
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you can install clang:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get install clang-6.0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not on Debian/Ubuntu, I am not sure whether or not there is another
solution than just compiling LLVM directly (see 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://clang.llvm.org/get_started.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we have the source and the compiler, so we are ready to compile. Go in
your linux-stable/ folder and:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;make CC=clang-6.0 -j4 bzImage
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just wanted the &lt;code&gt;bzImage&lt;/code&gt; to boot, but you remove it if you want to compile
everything.
&lt;code&gt;-j4&lt;/code&gt; because gain time by making compilation parallel&amp;hellip; Now I don&amp;rsquo;t know how you
plan to use your clang compiled kernel, but just to check it&amp;rsquo;s usable, I run it
with qemu:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;qemu-system-x86_64 -kernel arch/x86/boot/bzImage -nographic -serial mon:stdio -append &#39;console=ttyS0&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And since we didn&amp;rsquo;t provide the -initrd option, it will crash at the end with
something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---[ end Kernel panic - not syncing: VFS: Unable to mount root fs on unknown-block(0,0)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of guides on how to use your kernel, not the goal here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That will conclude my first post. Hopefully it was clear enough. Don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate
to contact me by any mean if you have any question or problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
