<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Edward J. Schwartz | Valentin Manès</title>
    <link>/authors/edward-j.-schwartz/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/edward-j.-schwartz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Edward J. Schwartz</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/profile_valentin.png</url>
      <title>Edward J. Schwartz</title>
      <link>/authors/edward-j.-schwartz/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Art, Science, and Engineering of Fuzzing: A Survey</title>
      <link>/publication/survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/survey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Among the many software testing techniques available today, &lt;em&gt;fuzzing&lt;/em&gt; has
remained highly popular due to its conceptual simplicity, its low barrier to
deployment, and its vast amount of empirical evidence in discovering real-world
software vulnerabilities.
At a high level, fuzzing refers to a process of repeatedly running a program
with generated inputs that may be syntactically or semantically malformed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8863940&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Our survey&lt;/a&gt; shows the fuzzing
community is extremely vibrant.
The recent surge of work by researchers and practitioners alike has made it
difficult to gain a comprehensive and coherent view of fuzzing. Thus, it is easy
to lose track of the design decisions and potentially important tweaks performed
in each tool and paper.
Furthermore, there has been an observable fragmentation in the terminology used
by various fuzzers. For example, test case &amp;ldquo;minimization&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;reduction&amp;rdquo;
are often used interchangeably. Such fragmentation makes it difficult to
discover and disseminate knowledge and may severely hinder the progress in
fuzzing research in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help preserve and bring coherence to the vast literature of fuzzing, this
paper presented a unified, general-purpose model of fuzzing together with a
taxonomy of the current literature.
Our terminology is chosen to closely reflect the current predominant usages, and
our model is designed to suit a large number of fuzzing tasks.
We surveyed academic papers from the major Security and Software Engineering
conferences in the last 10 years, as well as projects having more than 100 stars
on GitHub.
The paper methodically explores the design decisions at every stage of the model
by surveying the related literature and innovations that make modern-day fuzzers
effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;companion-website&#34;&gt;Companion Website&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our contribution in this work is more than just the survey. Upon receiving the
acceptance notice, we have started building 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://fuzzing-survey.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a companion
website&lt;/a&gt;. It is backed by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SoftSec-KAIST/Fuzzing-Survey&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a repository at
GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, which contains the
genealogy and the classification data of the surveyed fuzzers in the JSON
format. We plan to keep this site up-to-date periodically through investing our
own effort and accepting contributions from the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
body{ /* Normal  */
    font-size: 13pt;
}
&lt;/style&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
